The Second Invasion from Mars

June 1 (3 am.)

O this accursed conformist world!

Lord, on top of everything else - Artemis! Looks like she's gotten mixed up with that Nicostratus after all. That's what you call a daughter.... Well, so be it.

About one o'clock this morning I was awakened by a terrific but distant rumbling and was startled by an ominous play of red lights over the walls of my bedroom. The rumbling went on roaring and reverberating like the sound of an earthquake, so that the whole house shook, the window-panes rattled and the vials danced on the nightstand. I rushed in a fright to the window. In the north the sky was aflame: it seemed as if the earth was gaping out there beyond the horizon and spewing fountains of multicolored fire up to the very stars. But on the bench right under my window, those two, seeing and hearing nothing, all lit up by the infernal commotion and rocking with the subterranean tremors, were embracing each other and kissing full on the mouth. I immediately recognized Artemis and assumed that Charon had returned, that she was so glad to see him she was kissing him like a bride instead of leading him straight to the bedroom. A second later, in the light of the red sky, I recognized the illustrious foreign-made jacket of Mr. Nicostratus, and my heart sank. Such moments as these ruin a man's constitution. And yet you couldn't say that this hit me like a bolt from the blue. There had been rumors, hints, all sorts of little jokes. And still I was knocked dead.

Clutching my heart, completely at a loss what to do, I made my way in my bare feet to the living room and began to phone the police. But just try to get through to the police when you need them. The line at the station was busy for a long time, and when someone did answer, who should be on duty but Pandareus. I asked him what phenomenon was that observable on the horizon. He didn't know what a phenomenon was. I asked him, "Can you tell me what's happening on the northern horizon?" He tried to figure out where that might be. I was at my wit's end to explain it to him, when finally he caught on.

"Ah-h-h," he says, "you mean the big fire?" And he reported that some sort of burning had indeed been observed, but what kind of burning it was and what was being burned had not been determined as yet. The house was quaking, everything was creaking, people were on the street pitifully screaming about war, and this old horse's ass starts telling me that they'd just brought Minotaur into the station: he was dead drunk, he'd defiled the corner of Mr. Laomedon's estate, and he couldn't stand up or even fight.

"Are you going to do anything about it or not?" I interrupted him.

"That's what I'm trying to tell you, Mr. Apollo," says this ass, taking offense, "I have to make a report, and you're tying me up on the telephone. If you're all so upset about the fire..."

"What if it's a war?" I asked him.

"No, it's not a war," he declared. "I would've known."

"What if it's an eruption?" I asked. He didn't know what an eruption was. I couldn't stand it anymore and hung up. Sweaty all over from this conversation, I went back to the bedroom and put on my robe and slippers.

The rumbling seemed to have quieted down, but the flashing continued. Those two were no longer kissing or even sitting on the bench in each other's arms but were standing hand-in-hand where anyone could see them, since the fire lit up the horizon as bold as day. Only the light wasn't white, but reddish orange, with clouds the color of watery coffee drifting across it. The neighbors were running around in the street in whatever, Mrs. Eurydice was grabbing people by their pajamas and demanding to be saved, and only Myrtilus took a businesslike approach, rolled his truck out of the garage and along with his wife and sons set about loading his household possessions. It was a real panic, just as in the good old days - I hadn't seen one like it for a long time. But as for me, I understood that if an atomic war had broken out, you couldn't find a better place in the region than our town for hiding, waiting, sitting it out. And if it was an eruption, then it was occurring somewhere far away, so once again our town wasn't threatened. Besides, it was doubtful that it was an eruption. What kind of eruption could we have?

I went upstairs and tried to wake Hermione. It was the same old story: "Leave me alone, you sot. You shouldn't drink at night - I don't want to now...." And so on. Then I started telling her in a loud and convincing voice about the atomic war and the eruption, laying on the colors rather thick, since otherwise I would never get anywhere. This got through to her, she leaped out of bed, shoved me out of the way and dashed straight for the kitchen, grumbling: "I'm going to take a look, and then you'd better watch out...." Unlocking the cupboard, she examined the bottle of cognac. I kept cool. "Where'd you get yourself in this state?" she asked, sniffing at me suspiciously. "What den of iniquity did you go to tonight?"

But when she looked out the window and saw our neighbors half-dressed in the street, when she saw Myrtilus in his underdrawers propped up on his roof and peering through his field glasses to the north, she forgot about me. As it happened, the northern horizon had again sunk into silence and darkness, though you could still make out a cloud of smoke completely obscuring the stars. What can you say? My Hermione is no Mrs. Eurydice for you. A different age and a different upbringing. I'd barely managed to down a glass of cognac when she dragged out the suitcases and called to Artemis at the top of her voice. Go on and call her, call her, I thought bitterly, maybe she'll hear you.

At that moment Artemis appeared at the door to her room. Lord! Pale as death, shaking all over, but with her pajamas already on and curlers in her hair. She asks, "What is it? What are you all shouting about?"

You've got to admit it, she's got guts. If this phenomenon hadn't occurred, I'd never have found out anything, and Charon even less. Our eyes met, she smiled at me affectionately but with trembling lips, and I decided not to utter the words on the tip of my tongue. To calm myself down, I went to my room and began to pack my stamps. You tremble, I said to her mentally, you shake. You're lonely, scared and unprotected. But he didn't support you or protect you. He picked a flower of pleasure and ran off on his own business. No, my dear, when a man's without honor, he's without honor to the very end.

Meanwhile, as I expected, the panic was quickly subsiding. It became an ordinary night again, the earth no longer shook, the houses didn't creak. Someone had taken Mrs. Eurydice home. No one was shouting about war anymore, particularly since there wasn't anything more to shout about. Glancing out the window, I saw that the street was deserted, only one or two houses had their lights on and Myrtilus was still on his roof, standing out among the stars in his underpants. I called over to him and asked what he could see.

"Sure, sure," he said irritably. "Go to bed, snore. You snore, and they'll give it to you...."

I asked who "they" were.

"Sure, sure," responded Myrtilus. "You wise guys know it all. Along with your Pandareus. He's a fool, your Pandareus, and nothing else but."

Hearing about Pandareus, I decided to phone the police again. It took a long time to get through, but when at long last I did, Pandareus informed me that there was no special news, but as for the rest everything was in order, drunk Minotaur had been shot with a sedative, had his stomach cleaned out and dropped off to sleep. About the big fire, the burning had stopped a long time ago, especially since it turned out not to be burning at all, but a big holiday fireworks display. While I was trying to recall what holiday it was, Pandareus hung up. He really is stupid and revoltingly uneducated, and he always has been. It's strange to see people like that in our police force. Our policemen should be intellectuals, models for the youth, heroes to be emulated, people you can safely entrust not only with weapons and authority, but also with educational work. But Charon considers such a police force a "company of eggheads." He says no state would want my kind of police force because it would start arresting and reeducating the very people the state finds most useful, beginning with the Prime Minister and the Chief of Police. I don't know, I don't know, could be. But for the senior officer not to know what a phenomenon is and to act like a clod while performing his duties - who needs it?

Tripping over the suitcases, I made my way back to the cupboard and poured myself a glass of cognac just as Hermione came back in the kitchen. She said this was a madhouse, you couldn't depend on anybody here, the men were not men and the women not women. I'm a complete alcoholic, Charon lives here like a tourist and Artemis is a lily-white unfit for real life. And so on. Maybe someone would explain to her why she was awakened in the middle of the night and forced to get out the suitcases? I answered Hermione as best I could and sought refuge in my bedroom. I ached all over, and now I know for sure that my eczema will be worse tomorrow. I already feel like scratching, but so far I've been able to hold back.

About three o'clock the earth shook again. I could hear the noise of many engines and the grinding of metal. It turned out to be a column of military trucks and armored carriers full of troops moving past the house. They drove slowly, with dimmed headlights, and Myrtilus had latched onto some kind of armored vehicle and was trotting alongside, holding onto the lug of the hatchway and shouting something. I don't know what they answered him, but when the column had passed and he stood alone in the street, I called over to him and asked for the news.

"Sure, sure," said Myrtilus. "We know what kind of maneuvers these are. A bunch of wise guys riding around on my money." And finally I understood it all. Big military exercises are taking place - perhaps even with the use of atomic weapons. Big deal.

Lord, now if only I can get some sleep!

June 2

I itch all over. And above all I can't bring myself to have a talk with Artemis. I can't stand those excessively personal conversations, that intimate tone. Besides, how do I know what shell answer?

The devil knows what to do with daughters like this. If only I had an inkling of what she needs! She's got a husband, not some kind of puny egghead, but a real hunk of a man; he's no slob, no cripple, and no lecher either. Though he could be: the comptroller's niece looks at him suggestively and Thyone makes eyes at him. Everyone knows about it, not to mention the schoolgirls, the summer-cottage girls, or Madam Persephone, the cattiest she-cat of them all - no cat can stand up to her. But actually I do know what Artemis would answer.

"Daddikins," she'd say, "it's boring, it's all so deadly boring around here."

And you can't argue with that! A young, beautiful woman, no children, a model disposition: she ought to be whisked away in a whirlwind of amusements, dances, flirtations, and the like. But Charon, unfortunately, is one of those, what shall we call them, philosophizes. A thinker. Totalitarianism, fascism, managerialism, communism. Dancing is a sexual stimulant, guests are blabbermouths, one's worse than the other. Don't breathe a word about a game of four kings. Yet, when it comes to drinking, he's nobody's fool! Get five of his know-it-all friends around a table and put five bottles of cognac in front of them, and they'll go on deciding the world's affairs till dawn. The lass yawns and yawns, she slams the door and goes to bed. You call that life? I understand, a man needs something manly, but, on the other hand, a woman needs something womanly! No, I love my son-in-law, he's my son-in-law, so I love him. But how long can you go on deciding the world's affairs? And what difference do those discussions make? It's obvious: you can talk about fascism till you're blue in the face and you won't make a dint in it. Before you can take a breath, it'll slap an iron helmet on you and - forward, long live the leader! But stop paying attention to your young wife, and she'll pay you back in spades. No philosophizing will help you then. I understand, a cultured man must discuss abstruse subjects now and then, but you must keep things in proportion, gentlemen.

A wonderful morning today. (Temperature: +19° C, cloud cover: 1, wind from the south at .5 meters per second. I ought to run down to the meteorological bureau and fix my wind gauge, since I dropped it again.) After breakfast I decided that a sleeping dog gets no pension, so I went to the mayor's office to look into it. As I walked along, pleased by the peace and quiet, I suddenly saw a crowd on the corner of Freedom and Juniper streets. It turned out that Minotaur had driven his cistern through a jeweler's front window, and the people had gathered around to watch him, all dirty, puffy and drunk again since early morning, try to explain it to the traffic cop. He made such an unwholesome contrast to the bright and shining morning that I immediately fell in the dumps. Obviously the police shouldn't have let him out so early, they must've known he'd drink himself into a stupor once he got going. But, on the other hand, how could they not let him out, since he's the only honey-dipper in town? Here you have only two options: either you take up the reeducation of Minotaur and drown in filth, or you make a compromise in the name of hygiene.

Because of Minotaur I was held up, and when I got to The Five Spot all the boys had already assembled. I paid my fine, and then one-legged Polyphemus treated me to an excellent cigar in an aluminum case, which his oldest son Polycarpus, a lieutenant in the merchant marines, had sent to him for me. This Polycarpus once studied under me for several years, until he ran away to sea as a cabin boy. He was a lively lad, a playful scamp. When the scamp flew the city, Polyphemus almost took me to court, as if, so to say, the teacher had corrupted the child with his lectures on the vast multiplicity of worlds. Polyphemus is still certain that the sky is firm and satellites run around on it like cyclists in a circus. My demonstrations of the value of astronomy are beyond him: they were beyond him then, and they are just as far beyond him now.

The boys were talking about how the city comptroller had again misused funds allocated for the construction of the stadium. That makes it the seventh time already. We talked of ways to put a stop to it. Silenus shrugged his shoulders and asserted that nothing would do but a trial.

"Enough half-measures," he said. "An open trial. Gather the whole town at the foundation of the stadium and tie the embezzler to a pillory at the scene of his crime. Thank God," he repeated, "that our law is sufficiently flexible that the means of suppression can equal the seriousness of the crime."

"I would even say," remarked grouchy Paralus, "that our law is too flexible. The comptroller has been taken to court twice already, and both times our flexible law bent clean around him. But maybe you think it happened that way because he wasn't tried at the foundation, but in the town hall.,,

Morpheus, thinking it over carefully, said that from this day forward he'd never give the comptroller another shave and haircut. Let 'im go hairy.

"You're all stupid backsides," said Polyphemus. "You'll never get anywhere. He can just spit on the whole lot of you. He has his own cronies."

"That's exactly it," grouchy Paralus caught on, and he reminded us that in addition to the city comptroller there lived and flourished the city architect who had designed the stadium to the best of his abilities and now had a natural interest in seeing that the stadium, God forbid, not be built.

Calais the stutterer began to sputter and stammer, and having thus gained everyone's attention he recalled that he himself, Calais, had almost come to blows with the architect at the Flower Festival. This statement gave the discussion a decidedly new turn.

One-legged Polyphemus, as a veteran and a man not squeamish about blood, proposed that we jump both of them at the entrance to Madam Persephone's house and take them down a notch. In critical moments like these Polyphemus completely loses a hold on his tongue - the barracks language flows right out of him.

"Take the smelly bastards down a notch," he thundered. "Shovel away all that crap, crush their bones, polish 'em off!"

It's simply amazing how such speeches affect the boys. They all got furious and started waving their hands, and Calais sputtered and stammered more violently than ever, since he couldn't pronounce a word in his great agitation. But here grouchy Paralus, the only one of us to keep cool, noted that besides the comptroller and the architect, there still happened to be living in the city, in his summer residence, the best friend of these two - a certain Mr. Laomedon. At this everyone fell silent and began to puff on the cigars and cigarettes, which had gone out during the discussion, because you couldn't take Mr. Laomedon down a notch or polish him off so easily. And when in the settling silence Calais inadvertently burst out, finally, with his favorite curse - "S-s-sock 'em in the snoot!" - everyone looked at him with displeasure.

I remembered that I should have gone to the mayor's office a long time before, so I inserted the remainder of my cigar into the aluminum case and went up to the second floor, to the reception room of Mr. Mayor. I was struck by the unusual bustle of the office. All the employees were excited somehow. Even Mr. Secretary, instead of examining his fingernails as usual, was busy imprinting wax seals on large envelopes, although, to be sure, with an expression of distaste and obligation. Feeling very out of place, I approached this fashionably slicked-down beauty. Lord, I'd give anything on earth to have nothing to do with him, neither to see him nor to hear him. Even before this I hadn't liked Mr. Nicostratus, just as I didn't like any of our town dandies. To tell the truth, I didn't like him even when he studied under me, because he was lazy, crude and insolent. But after yesterday it makes me sick just to look at him. I had no idea what tone to take with him. But there was no getting out of it, and finally I decided to say "Mr. Nicostratus, have you heard anything concerning my case?"

He didn't even glance at me, didn't even, so to say, favor me with a glance. "Sorry, Mr. Apollo, but the answer hasn't come in yet from the ministry," he said, continuing to press the seals. I hung around a moment and then headed for the exit, feeling rotten, as I always do in official places. However, quite unexpectedly, he stopped me with a surprising piece of news. He said there had been no communication with Marathon since yesterday.

"What are you saying!" said I. "Haven't the maneuvers ended yet?"

"What maneuvers?" he asked in surprise.

Here I lost my composure. I still don't know if I should have done it, but I stared straight at him and said, "What do you mean - 'what maneuvers?' The same ones you happened to see last night."

"So they were maneuvers, were they?" he declared with enviable indifference, again bending over his envelopes. "They were fireworks. Read the morning papers."

I should have, I really should have said a couple of words to him, especially since at that moment we were alone in the room. But can I be like that?

When I returned to The Five Spot, an argument was underway about the nature of last night's phenomenon. Our number had grown: Myrtilus and Pandareus had joined us. Pandareus had the jacket of his uniform unbuttoned; he was unshaven and tired after his night duty. Myrtilus didn't look any better, because he had spent the entire night patrolling the grounds around his house, expecting the worst. Everyone had the morning paper in hand, and they were discussing the column of "our observer," which bore the following heading: holiday in the offing.

"Our observer" reported that Marathon was preparing to commemorate its 153rd anniversary. From his usually well-informed sources he had learned that last night there had been a fireworks practice which residents of the surrounding towns and villages within a radius of up to two hundred kilometers had been able to enjoy.

That's all that was needed! Charon goes away on assignment, and our newspaper falls into catastrophic stupidity. They should at least have tried to figure out what a fireworks display would look like from two hundred kilometers away. And they should at least have asked themselves when fireworks displays began to be accompanied by subterranean tremors. I immediately explained this to the boys, but they answered that they knew perfectly well the time of day and advised me to read The Milesian Herald. In the Herald it was printed black on white that last night "the Milesians could admire the impressive spectacle of military exercises employing the latest devices of war technology."

"What did I tell you!" I burst out, but Myrtilus interrupted me. He related that early this morning an unknown driver from the Long-Distance Transport Company had driven up to his pump, had gotten 150 liters of gas, two cans of motor oil, and a crate of marmalade and had told him, in secret, that last night, for reasons unknown, the underground rocket-fuel factories had exploded. Supposedly the 23 guards and the entire night shift had perished, and 179 more men had vanished without a trace. This news threw us all into a panic, but then grouchy Paralus put forward the question "What then, I'd like to know, did he need the marmalade for?"

This question stumped Myrtilus. "Sure, sure," he said, "you heard it. That's all you're getting out of me."

We also had nothing to say. Really, what has marmalade got to do with it? Calais sputtered, sprayed, but didn't say anything. And then that old horse's ass, Pandareus, took the floor.

"Listen, old boys," says he, "those weren't any rocket factories. They were marmalade factories, obviously. Now, behave yourselves."

We sat down.

"Underground marmalade factories?" says Paralus. "Well, old-timer, you're in superb form today."

We began to slap Pandareus on the back, adding, "Yes, Pan, one can see right away that you slept poorly today, old-timer. Minotaur has run you ragged, Pan, it's a hard life. Time you took your pension, Pan, good old boy!"

"A policeman, and he plants the seeds of panic himself," said Myrtilus, highly offended. He was the only one who had taken Pandareus's words seriously.

"That's why he's Pan - to plant seeds everywhere," quipped Dymus. And Polyphemus also made a successful quip, although a completely indecent one. We went on amusing ourselves in this fashion, while Pandareus stood stock-still, then puffed himself up before our very eyes and tossed his head from side to side like a bull taunted by matadors.

Finally he buttoned his jacket up to the very last button, set his eyes above our heads and bawled: "You've had your say - enough! Dis-s-sperse! In the name of the law." Myrtilus went back to his gas pump, and the rest of us headed for the tavern.

In the tavern we all immediately ordered beer. This is a satisfaction I was denied until I went on my pension! In such a small town as ours, everyone knows the teacher. The parents of your pupils imagine for some reason that you are a wonder-worker and are able by your personal example to keep the children from following in their parents' footsteps. From morning to night the tavern literally swarms with these parents, but if you permit yourself an innocent mug of beer, then the next day without fail you will have a humiliating conversation with the principal. And yet I love the tavern! I love to sit in the company of good men, having leisurely and serious conversations on subjects of your choice, half catching the drone of voices and the clinking of glasses behind your back. I love to tell and to hear a salty little story, to play four kings - for a small amount, but with honor, and when I win I like to order a mug for everyone. Well, enough.

Iapetus served us our beer, and we began talking about the war. One-legged Polyphemus declared that if this were a war, they would already be mobilizing the troops, but grouchy Paralus objected that if it were a war, we wouldn't know anything about it. I don't like conversations about war and would gladly have turned the conversation to pensions, but who am I to do this?

Polyphemus laid his crutch across the table and asked what, in fact, did Paralus know about wars. "Do you know, for example, what a bazooka is?" he asked threateningly.

"Do you know what it means to sit in a trench when the tanks are coming at you and you haven't yet noticed that you've dumped in your drawers?"

Paralus objected that he didn't know anything about tanks and dumping in your drawers and he didn't want to know anything about them, but as for nuclear war we all knew the same thing about it. "You lie down with your feet in the blast and crawl to the nearest graveyard," he said.

"You were born a civvy and you'll die a civvy," said one-legged Polyphemus. "Nuclear war - that's a war of nerves, understand? They do us, we do them, and the first one to dump in his drawers loses." Paralus only shrugged his shoulders, and Polyphemus lost his temper completely. "Bazookas!" he yelled. "Tarzons! Ready, aim - dump in your drawers! Right, Apollo?"

Having shouted to his heart's content, he launched into recollections about how he and our troops had repelled a tank attack in the snow. I can't stand these recollections. Nothing but dump in your drawers. I don't know, maybe it all happened, I don't recall. But still I don't like to return to it. Polyphemus was gung-ho then, and he's gung-ho now. I simply don't know what you must take out of a man to make him stop being a noncommissioned officer. Maybe the problem is that he never happened to get caught in a pocket, as I did. Or is it a matter of character?

We had sat a long time, so I decided to go ahead and have lunch. Usually the fare at Iapetus's place is pretty good, but this time the chef's soup with dumplings gave off a heavy odor of cheap olive oil, and I told him about it. It turned out that Iapetus's teeth had been aching for three days, so unbearably that he couldn't prepare anything properly.

"Don't you remember, Phoebus, how I once knocked your tooth in?" he asked mournfully.

How could I not remember! It was in the seventh grade. We were both courting Iphigenia and we fought every day. My God, how distant are the times when I could have a good scrap! Iphigenia, it happens, is now married to some engineer in the south; she already has grandchildren and angina pectoris.

While on my way to Achilles' place, I passed Mr. Laomedon's house with that terrible red car of his with bulletproof windows standing outside. At the wheel that insolent punk who always makes fun of me was smoking himself silly. And this time he lit into me so viciously that I was obliged to cross the street in a dignified manner and pay not the slightest attention to him. Achilles was presiding over the cash register and looking through his Cosmos, Ever since he obtained that blue triangle with the little silver postage mark, he has made it a rule to take out his album just as I enter, as if by coincidence. I can see right through him, but I don't let on. Although, to tell the truth, every time he does it my heart contracts. My only consolation is that part of his triangle is glued on. I mentioned it to him.

"Yes," said I, "there's no denying it, Achilles, it's a nice item. Too bad, though, that it's glued together."

He squinted all over and mumbled that the grapes, it seemed, were sour.

"What can you do?" I answered him calmly. "Glued together is glued together, you can't get around it. I personally wouldn't have taken the stamp at that price. But some people, of course," said I, "are so broad-minded that they'll take stamps that are canceled and glued together. That's not for me, no kidding. I'd take them only for trading. You can always find some simpleton who doesn't care if they're glued together or not."

That'll teach you to stick your silver postmark under my nose!

But otherwise we had a good time together. He tried to persuade me that yesterday's fireworks were a rare type of northern lights which accidentally coincided with a special type of earthquake, and I informed him of the maneuvers and the explosion at the marmalade factory. It's impossible to argue with Achilles. Because you can see that the man doesn't believe in his own words, but still persists in arguing. He sits there like some Mongolian stone image, looks out the window and repeats the same thing over and over again, that Fm not the only one in town who can interpret the phenomena of nature. You'd think that in their pharmaceutical school they would actually train people in the serious sciences. But no, it's impossible to bring an argument with any one of the boys to a reasonable conclusion. Take Polyphemus, for example. He never argues to the heart of the matter. Truth doesn't interest him, for him only one thing is important: disgracing his opponent. Say that we're arguing about the shape of our planet. Employing the precise arguments known to every educated person, I prove to him that the Earth is, to put it crudely, a ball. He savagely and unsuccessfully attacks every argument in turn, and when we come to the shape of the Earth's shadow during a lunar eclipse, he comes out with something like this: "A shadow, a shadow! You bring in a shadow in the broad daylight. First show the beard under your nose and grow the hair on your bald spot before you start arguing about the world." Or take Paralus. I once argued with him about ways to cure alcoholism. I hadn't had time to bat my eyes before we had turned to the foreign policy of our president, and from there - to the problem of panspermia. And the most surprising thing is that I had and still have nothing to do with either panspermia or foreign policy, it's simply that Hermione's cousin's son suffered from alcoholism and tormented everyone around him. Now he's a medic in the army, but at that time my life was an absolute nightmare. Yes, alcoholism is the scourge of the people.

Our argument ended with Achilles taking out his trusty bottle and our drinking a shot of gin. Achilles' business isn't going very well. I have the impression that he wouldn't even have enough for gin if it weren't for Madam Persephone. Someone came from her place again today.

"I can recommend an antihistamine," said Achilles in a discreet whisper.

"No," answers the messenger girl, "something more reliable was requested, please."

Something more reliable, you see, for her. The little cook from Iapetus's place ran in too, for tooth drops, but no one else came, and we talked our fill. I traded a pink "Monument" for his "Red Cross" series. Actually, I don't need "Red Cross," but the day before yesterday Charon told me that he'd received a personal announcement at the editorial offices, which read:

Will take "Red Cross." Offer any inverted postmark from the standard set.

I must confess that, strange as it seems, Charon is the only person in our house who doesn't giggle at me. In general, if you think about it, he's not such a bad fellow. Artemis is acting not only immorally, but also ignobly. And with the likes of Nicostratus!

Returning home at nine in the evening, I saw them again sitting in my garden, in the shadows. True, they weren't kissing this time, but still they ought to have a sense of decency. I went in the garden, took Artemis by the hand and said to that dandy, "Goodbye, Mr. Nicostratus, pleasant dreams." Artemis yanked her hand away from me^ and walked away without a word. And that rake, very ineptly trying to smooth over the awkward situation, struck up a conversation with me about the municipal recommendations which need to be attached to the request for a pension. And so I stand there and listen to him. I ought to drive him from the garden with a stick, but I listen to him. That damned delicacy of mine. And lack of confidence. I really have an inferiority complex.

And then he gave me a nasty smirk and said, "And how is charming Mrs. Hermione getting along? You didn't miss your mark there, Mr. Apollo. I wouldn't have refused such a housekeeper myself."

My heart sank and I lost the power of speech. But without waiting for an answer (what did he need my answer for?}, he went off, laughing all the way down the street. I remained alone in the dark garden.

No, there's nothing you can do about it. Still, relations between me and Hermione ought to be put in order. I know I won't get anywhere, but peace of mind requires sacrifices.

June 3

Sometimes I am seized with utter horror when I think that the matter of my pension is not progressing. Everything tightens up inside me, and I can't apply myself to anything.

But if you think it out logically, the matter should come to the most beneficial conclusion. First of all, I worked as a teacher for thirty years, not counting the break for the war. To be more precise, thirty years and two months. Second, I did not change my place of work even once, I never interrupted my term of service with transfers and other distracting circumstances, and only once, seven years ago, did I take a short leave of absence at my own expense. And participation in military activities cannot be considered a break in service, that's clear. By my best calculation, more than four thousand students passed through my classes, almost all of the present townspeople. Third, in recent years I have been constantly before the public and three times have substituted for the gymnasium director during his leave. Fourth, my work has been flawless; I have sixteen statements of gratitude from the ministry, a personal letter from the late minister on my fiftieth birthday, and likewise a bronze medal "For diligent work in the fallow field of public education." A whole compartment of my desk is specially set aside for letters of thanks from parents. Fifth, my speciality: today everything has turned topsy-turvy in this Cosmos; thus astronomy has become a timely subject. In my opinion, this is also a point in my favor. So, if you only glance at the matter, it would seem there could hardly be any doubt. In the minister's place I would certainly put me in the first-class category, without a moment's hesitation. Lord, then I could finally rest easy. After all, when you get right down to it, I don't need a lot in life. Three to four cigarettes, a glass of cognac, a pittance for cards, that's all. Along with stamps, of course. First class - that means 150 a month. One hundred I'll give to Hermione for household expenses; twenty goes into savings for a rainy day, and what's left is mine. That's enough for stamps and the rest. Really, haven't I earned it?

It's too bad that no one needs an old man. Squeeze him out like a lemon and then - kick off. Letters of gratitude? Who cares about them now? Medals? Who doesn't have them? And someone is bound to latch onto the fact that I was a prisoner. Were you a prisoner? I was. Three years? Three years. That's all! Your service was interrupted for three years, take your third-class pension and don't drag out our correspondence.

If only I had connections! Actually there is one student of mine, General Alcimus by name, who now sits in the Lower Congress. What if I write him? He ought to remember me, he and I had many of those little conflicts which students love to recall when they have grown up. By God, I will write him.

I'll start right off: "Hi, boy. I'm an old man now-----" No, I'll wait a bit and then write.

All day today I sat at home. Yesterday Hermione visited an aunt and brought back a big package of old stamps. I derived great pleasure from rummaging through them.

There's nothing like it. It's like an endless honeymoon. Several fine specimens turned up, true, all of them glued to something. I'll have to restore them. Myrtilus has pitched a tent in his yard and is living there with his whole family. He was boasting that he could get up and go within ten minutes. He went on that there was still no communication with Marathon. He's probably lying. Drunken Minotaur drove his filthy cistern into Mr. Laomedon's red car and got into a fight with the chauffeur. Both of them were taken to the station. Minotaur was thrown in jail to sober up, and the chauffeur, so they say, was sent to the hospital. So there is justice in the world after all. Artemis is sitting as quiet as a mouse: Charon should be returning any time now. I haven't told Hermione anything about it. Maybe it will all blow over. But boy, I'd like to get first class!

June 4

Just finished reading the evening papers, but just as before I don't understand anything. No doubt about it, some sort of changes have taken place. But what kind exactly? People around here like to tell whoppers, that's all.

This morning, after my coffee, I set off for The Five Spot. It was a good morning, warm. (Temperature: +18° C, cloud cover: 0, wind from the south at 1 meter per second by my wind gauge.) Coming through the gate, I saw Myrtilus fussing over his tent, which lay crumbled up on the ground. I asked him what he was doing.

"Sure, sure," he answered in extreme irritation. "You wise guys know it all. Just sit still and wait until they cut us all up." I don't believe Myrtilus any farther than I can throw him, but he always gives me the creeps when he talks like this.

"And what else is new?" I ask.

"Martians," he replied curtly and continued to smooth out the tent with his knee. I didn't understand him at first and maybe that's why I got such a funny feeling from that word, as if something terrible and unstoppable were on the way.

My legs went weak and I slumped back on the bumper of the truck. Myrtilus said nothing, only huffed and puffed.

"What'd you say?" I asked.

He packed up the tent, tossed it in the back of the truck and lit up a smoke. "The Martians have attacked," he said in a whisper. "It's the end of us all. They burned Marathon down to the ground, I hear. Ten million killed in one night, can you believe it? Today they paid a visit to our mayor's office. The power's theirs now, and that's that. They've already prohibited any planting, and now, I hear, they're going to slit open everybody's stomach. They need stomachs for some reason, can you believe it? I'm not going to wait for that, I need my stomach myself. As soon as I heard about it, I decided right away: these new rulings are not for me, they can all take a flying leap, 'cause I'm heading to my brother's farm. I've already sent the old lady and the kids on the bus. We'll sit it out, keep our eyes open, and see how things are going from there."

"Hold on," I said, keenly remembering how he always lies, but feeling myself getting weaker. "Hold on, Myrtilus, what are you talking about? Who attacked? Who burned? My son-in-law's in Marathon right now."

"Your son-in-law's had it," Myrtilus said sympathetically and flicked away his butt. "Consider your daughter a widow, The secretary has a clear road ahead. Well, I'm off. So long, Apollo. We were always on good terms. I've got no hard feelings toward you, so don't think badly of me."

"Lord!" I burst out in desperation, completely weakened. "Who was it that attacked?"

"Martians, Martians!" he said, again switching to a whisper. "From there!" He raised his finger to the sky. "They jumped in on us from a comet."

"You mean men from Mars?" I asked with a glimmer of hope.

"Sure, sure," he said, climbing into the cabin. "You're a teacher, you know better. But it's all the same to me who pokes out my guts."

"Lord, Myrtilus," I said, finally catching on that this was all a bunch of lies. "You can't go on like this. You're an elderly man, you have grandchildren. How can there be any men from Mars, when Mars is a lifeless planet? There's no life there, that's a scientific fact."

"Sure, sure," Myrtilus went on lying, but it was obvious that he was beginning to have doubts. "And what other facts are there about it?"

"Well, it's not 'sure, sure'; it's the way it actually is," I said. "Ask any scientist. But who needs a scientist, this is something every schoolboy knows!"

Myrtilus grunted and climbed out of the cabin. "It can all take a flying leap!" he said, laying his fingers on the back of his head. "Who am I to listen to? Am I to listen to you? Or to Pandareus? I don't understand a thing." He spat and went into his house.

I also decided to go back in, in order to phone the police. Pandareus, as it happened, was very busy, because Minotaur had broken out of his cell and Pandareus had to form a search party. It was true that someone, some kind of leaders, had driven to the mayor's office about an hour and a half before, and they might have been Martians, there were rumors that they were Martians, but as far as cutting open stomachs was concerned, no word had been given, and anyway he had no time for Martians, because Minotaur alone, in his opinion, was worse than all the Martians put together.

I hurried to The Five Spot.

Almost all the boys were crowding at the entrance to the mayor's office and arguing furiously about some kind of tracks in the dirt. The tracks had been made by the Martian who had come, they knew this for a fact. Morpheus asserted that he, as an old hairdresser and masseur, had never seen such marvels before. "Spiders," he was saying, "huge hairy spiders. That is, the males are hairy, but the females are naked. They walk on their back feet and grab you with their front. Did you see the prints? Horrifying! Like holes in the ground. That's where he walked by."

"He didn't just walk by," said Silenus thoughtfully. "The force of gravity is greater on Earth, as Apollo here will confirm, so that they can't simply walk with their legs. They need special stilts with springs, and that's what made the holes in the ground."

"Right, stilts," seconded Iapetus indistinctly with his bandaged-up jaw. "Only they're not stilts. They have a certain kind of car, I saw it in the movies. It doesn't run on wheels, but on levers, on stilts."

"Our comptroller has gone off the deep end again," said grouchy Paralus. "The last time it was a hail storm of unusual force, and the time before that he announced locusts, but now he's whipped up Martians - in keeping with the times, the conquest of space."

"I can't look at these tracks without getting excited," repeated Morpheus. "Horrifying. What d'ya say, buddies, let's go have a drink."

Calais stammered, sputtered and shook. Finally he pronounced: "G-g-good weather we're having, old boys! How d-d-did you sleep?" Due to his speech defect he always lags behind events. And yet he's a veterinarian; he could have said something worthwhile about the tracks.

"Myrtilus has already packed off," said Dymus, giggling stupidly. " 'Goodbye, Dymus,' he says, 'we were always on good terms. Look after my gas pump,' he says, 'and if you have to, burn it,' he says, 'so we leave nothing to the enemy.' "

Here I cautiously inquired what had been heard about Marathon.

"They say Marathon was burned down," Dymus answered readily. "They say people phoned from there with the terms for peace."

This absolutely convinced me that all of this was a bunch of senseless rumors, and I was getting ready to refute them when the wailing of a police siren cut through the air and we all turned around.

Minotaur came running across the square, staggering and zigzagging like a bunny, splattered with mud and swollen, and hot on his heels came Pandareus in his police buggy, standing up and holding onto the windshield, shouting something and waving a pair of handcuffs.

"The jig's up, he'll catch him now," said Morpheus.

"That's what you think," objected Dymus. "See what he's doing?"

Minotaur ran up to a telephone pole, threw his arms and legs around it and began to scramble up. However, Pandareus had already jumped out of the vehicle and fastened onto his pants. With the help of a subordinate, he tore the honey-dipper away from the pole, packed him into the buggy, and put on the handcuffs. After this the subordinate drove away, and Pandareus, wiping his face with a handkerchief and buttoning himself up on the way, headed toward us.

"Got 'im," reported Morpheus, addressing Dymus. "You argue over everything."

Pandareus drew near and asked what was new with us. He was told of the Martian tracks. He immediately squatted down and became engrossed in an investigation of the matter. I even felt an involuntary twinge of respect for him, because right away you could see his true professional knack: he looked at the tracks sort of from the side and didn't touch anything with his fingers. I began to expect that everything would soon be cleared up. Pandareus moved alongside the tracks like a duck wagging its extruding backside

and kept repeating: "Aha.... That's clear.... Aha.... Clear...." We waited impatiently, preserving silence, and only Calais strained to say something and sputtered. Finally Pandareus straightened up with a groan and, looking over the square as if to spy someone, pronounced in short bursts: "Two of them. Took the money in a bag. One has a cane with a spike. The other smokes Astras."

"I also smoke Astras," said grouchy Paralus, and Pandareus glared at him.

"Two of whom?" asked Dymus. "Martians?"

"Right from the start I thought they were not our sort," said Pandareus slowly, not taking his eyes off of Paralus. "Right from the start I thought these fellows were from Milesia. I know them."

Here Calais burst out: "N-n-no, he won't catch him in that buggy."

"But what about the Martians?" said Dymus. "I don't understand. ..."

Pandareus, ignoring direct questions as before, looked Paralus up and down. "Hand me your cigarette, old man," he said.

"What d'ya need it for?" asked Paralus.

"I'd like to take a look at your bite," explained Pandareus, "and also, where were you today between six and seven in the morning?"

We looked at Paralus, and he said that in his opinion Pandareus was the biggest fool in the world, not counting the cretin who allowed him into the police force. We had to agree with him and started slapping Pandareus on the back, saying, "Yeah, Pandareus, you missed by a mile. You didn't know, Pan, old boy, that these were Martian tracks. But, of course, how could you know, old buddy, about Martians? They're not your usual honey-dippers, Pan!"

Pandareus began to puff up a bit, but here one-legged Polyphemus came out of the mayor's office and cut right into our enjoyment.

"It's a dirty business, boys!" he said in a troubled voice. "The Martians are attacking, they took Milesia! Our forces are retreating, burning the crops, blowing up the bridges behind them!"

My legs felt weak again and I didn't have the strength to push my way through to a bench and sit down.

"They've put down a landing party in the south: two divisions," croaked Polyphemus. "They'll be here soon!"

"They've already been here," said Silenus. "On special stilts. There are their tracks over there...."

Polyphemus merely took a glance and said in disgust that those were his tracks, and everyone realized at once that, in fact, they were. Not even his, but his crutch's. For me it was a big relief. But Pandareus, as soon as it got around to him, buttoned his jacket up to the last button, cast his eyes over our heads and bawled: "You've had your say - that's all! Dis-s-sperse! In the name of the law."

I went into the mayor's office. The place was packed with some kind of flat bags set along the walls in the corridors, the stair landings and even the reception room. The bags gave off an unfamiliar smell and the windows were wide open everywhere, but other than that everything was normal. Mr. Nicostratus was sitting at his desk and polishing his nails. Grinning in a vague way and speaking with a very dubious intonation, he gave me to understand that the duties of his position did not give him the right to enlarge on Martians, however he could definitely state that all this hardly had any connection with the question of my pension. Only one thing was certain: it would no longer be profitable to plant wheat in these parts, but it would be profitable to plant a certain new kind of nutritive grain which had, as he put it, universal properties. The seeds were stored in those bags, and from today on they would begin to distribute them to all the neighboring farms.

"Where did the bags come from?" I asked.

"Supplied," he answered weightily.

I overcame my diffidence and inquired who supplied them.

"Official persons," he said. He raised himself from behind his desk, excused himself and took himself with his loose amble into the mayor's office.

I went into the general offices and chatted awhile with the typists and the watchman. Strange as it may seem, they confirmed almost all the rumors about the Martians, but did not leave me with the impression that they were truly informed. Oh, I've had it with these rumors! No one believes in them, but everyone repeats them. It goes so far that even the simplest facts are distorted. Like the blown-up bridges of Polyphemus. What actually happened? Polyphemus had been the first to arrive at The Five Spot. They saw him from the window and asked him into the general offices to repair a typewriter. While he was laboring, regaling the girls with stories of how his leg had been ripped off, Mr. Mayor came in, stood a moment, listened with a thoughtful expression and then uttered an enigmatic phrase: "Yes, ladies and gentlemen, it's evident that the bridges are burned out.,, And then he returned to his office, where he immediately ordered sardine sandwiches and a bottle of Phargossa beer. Polyphemus went on to tell the girls that in a retreat you usually blow up the bridges behind you in order to thwart the enemy. The rest is obvious. What stupidity! I considered it my duty to inform the employees of the mayor's office that Mr. Mayor's mysterious phrase signified only that a decision had been taken which could not be changed. Naturally, all their faces immediately expressed relief, mixed with a touch of disappointment.

No one was at The Five Spot, as Pandareus had driven them all away. Almost completely calmed down, I went over to Achilles to tell him about my new acquisitions and to test the water in regard to the architecture series: perhaps he would take a canceled one, since he couldn't get a clean one in any event. After all, he even takes them glued together. However, Achilles was also feeling the pressure of the spreading rumors. In answer to my proposal, he said absent-mindedly that he'd think about it, and at that moment, without even noticing it, he gave me a brilliant idea.

"The Martians," he said, "are a new regime. And as you know, Phoebus, a new regime means new stamps."

I was amazed that this simple thought had not entered my own head. That's right, if the rumors are only partly true, the first reasoned act of these mythical Martians would be to issue their own new stamps, or at least to print over our old ones. I said goodbye to Achilles hastily and headed straight for the post office.

Well, of course, there had been no correspondence with new stamps and nothing new at all at the post office. When will we ever learn to stop believing in rumors? For it is well known that Mars has an extremely thin atmosphere, its climate is excessively severe and almost lacks water, the basis of all life. The myths about the canals were thrown overboard a long time ago, since the canals turned out to be nothing more than an optical illusion. In brief, all this recalls the panic of the year before last, when one-legged Polyphemus ran around town with a fowling piece shouting that a gigantic man-eating triton has escaped from the zoo. That time Myrtilus cleverly managed to get his whole household out of the city, and he didn't decide to come back for two weeks.

The twilight reason of my uneducated compatriots, spoiled by a monotonous life, gives birth to truly fantastic spectres at the slightest disturbance. Our world is like a chicken coop sunk in nocturnal slumber, where you need only accidentally brush against the feather of some colorful old bird snoozing on his perch for the whole place to be thrown into indescribable confusion, with fluttering, clucking and slinging of muck in every direction. Life is already disturbing enough, in my opinion, without all that. We should all keep a check on our nerves. I've read that rumors are much more dangerous to health than even smoking. The author proved it with facts and figures. It was also written there that the force of a panic-rumor is directly proportional to the ignorance of the mass, and this is true, although it must be admitted that even the very best educated among us submit with surprising ease to the general mood and are ready to run with the stupefied crowd wherever their noses lead them.

I had intended to explain this to the boys, but on the way to the tavern I noticed that a crowd had again formed at The Five Spot. I stopped off and discovered that the rumors had already exerted their pernicious influence. No one was willing to listen to my considerations on the matter. Everyone was aroused beyond all bounds, and the veterans shook firearms fresh from the grease pack and still not properly cleaned. I learned that the soldiers of the Eighty-eighth infantry had been discharged and expelled from their barracks. These soldiers told an incomprehensible story.

The night before last the regiment had been summoned by alarm and put on full military alert; they spent some time, until morning in fact, sitting in armored carriers and trucks on the parade grounds. In the morning the alert was called off, and yesterday passed in the normal fashion. But last night the same thing happened again, with this difference: this morning a colonel came from headquarters by helicopter, ordered the regiment to line up for punishment and without getting out of his helicopter delivered a long and completely incomprehensible speech, after which he flew away and almost the entire regiment was relieved of duty. It must be said that the soldiers, having slaked their thirst royally at Iapetus's place, spoke most inarticulately and now and then struck up the famous bawdy song:

Nioba-Niobe-ya, always willing to obey-ya ...

However, it was clear that the colonel from headquarters had not said a word about Martians. He had spoken, in fact, about only two things: the soldier's patriotic duty and his stomach juice. Somehow he had managed to combine these two concepts in a manner which couldn't be grasped. The soldiers themselves couldn't make head or tail of these subtleties, but they did understand that after this morning anyone the sergeant caught with Narco chewing gum or Opi cigarettes would be tossed in the brig for ten days and rot there. Immediately after the colonel's departure, the regimental commander, not countermanding the punishment, ordered the junior officers and sergeants to conduct a meticulous search through the barracks to remove all cigarettes and chewing gum containing stimulants. The soldiers knew no more than this, and indeed they didn't want to know more. Grabbing each other by the shoulders, they stormed with such threatening looks,

Nioba-Niobe-ya, how I want ya, baby ...

that we hastily withdrew and left them.

Here Polyphemus with his crutch and fowling piece lumbered up on a bench and began to shout that the generals had betrayed us, spies were all around us and true patriots should rally round the flag, because patriotism and so on. Polyphemus can't live without patriotism. He can live without legs, but without patriotism he can't make it. When he had shouted himself hoarse and shut up in order to have a smoke, I tried in any event to elucidate some things for the boys. I began by saying that there was no life on Mars and could not possibly be - it was all imaginary. But again they would not let me speak. First Morpheus stuck the morning paper from the capital under my nose. It had a big article, "Is There Life on Mars?" In this article all previous scientific data were subjected to ironical doubt. But when I was not set back and attempted to debate the matter, Polyphemus elbowed his way up to me, grabbed me by the collar and hoarsely threatened: "Blunting our vigilance, you plague? Martian spy, bald-headed turd! To the wall with you!,,

I can't bear it when people address me that way. My heart began to pound, and I yelled for the police. What a hooligan! I won't forgive Polyphemus for the rest of my life. Who does he think he is! I tore away, called him a one-legged swine and went to the tavern.

It was nice to find that not only I considered Polyphemus's patriotic yelps repellent. Two or three of our boys were already in the tavern. They were sitting around Cronidus the archivist, pouring him rounds of beer and inquiring about the morning visit of the Martians.

"What's so big about Martians?" said Cronidus, rolling the whites of his eyes with difficulty. "They're Martians like any other Martians. One's called Calchas, the other Eleius, both of them southerners, with such noses on them...."

"Well, what about their car?" they asked him.

"It's a car like any other car, it's black and flies. . .. Nope, not a helicopter. It flies, that's all. What do you think I am, a pilot? How am I supposed to know how it flies?"

I had lunch, waited for them to leave him alone, took two shots of gin and sat down next to him.

"Heard anything new about pensions?" I asked.

However, Cronidus had already lost control of his faculties. His eyes watered, he simply downed one shot after another like an automatic machine and mumbled: "Martians are Martians, one's Calchas, the other's Eleius.... Black, they fly... Nope, not blimps.... Eleius, I say.... Not me, a pilot...." Then he fell asleep.

When Polyphemus roared into the tavern with his gang, I made a show of leaving for home. Myrtilus hadn't gone. He'd pitched his tent again and was sitting and cooking supper on a gas stove. Artemis wasn't home, she'd gone off somewhere without saying where, and Hermione was cleaning the rugs. To calm myself, I worked on restoring my stamps. It's nice anyway to think what mastery I have achieved. I don't know if anyone would be able to distinguish the glue I applied from the original stuff. In any event, Achilles can't.

Now about today's newspapers. Remarkable papers nowadays. Almost all the columns are filled with the reflections of various medical men about the most reasonable diets. Medical preparations containing opium, morphine and caffeine are spoken of with an extreme and somehow unnatural indignation. What is this, am I supposed to suffer if my liver begins to ache? Not one paper has a philately section, there's not a word about soccer, but all the papers reprint a gigantic and completely vapid article about the significance of gastric juice. Without them, I guess, I wouldn't understand the significance of gastric juice. Not one telegram from abroad, not a word about the consequences of the embargo; instead, they draw out a dumb discussion about wheat. Supposedly there are not enough vitamins in wheat; wheat supposedly is too easily infected by harmful agents. A certain Marsyas, an M.A. in agriculture, has come to the conclusion that the millennium-old history of cultivating wheat and other useful grains (oats, corn, maize) has been a universal mistake of mankind, one which, however, it is not too late to correct. I don't know anything about wheat, the specialists are more qualified, but the article is written in an insufferably critical, I would even say prejudiced, tone. It's obvious at a glance that this Marsyas is a typical southerner, a nihilist and fault-finder.

It's twelve o'clock already, and Artemis still isn't home. She hasn't come back, she can't be seen in the garden, and meanwhile the streets are filled with drunken soldiers. She might at least have phoned where she was. I keep waiting for Hermione to come in and ask what has happened to Artemis. I have no idea what I'll answer. I don't like such conversations, I can't stand them. You might ask who my daughter takes after. Her late mother was a very modest woman; only one time was she attracted to the city architect, but it was just an attraction - two or three notes, one letter. I myself was never a gay dog, as Polyphemus would put it. I still remember my visit to Madam Persephone's house with horror. No, such a pastime is not meant for a civilized man. Whatever you may say, love, even the physical kind, is a mystery, and to practice love in the company of people you even know well and who wish you well is not so amusing as certain books make it out to be. God forbid, I'm not thinking, of course, that my Artemis is reveling in bacchanalian dances amid bottles of booze at this moment, but she might at least have called. You can only be amazed at the stupidity of my son-in-law. In his place I would have returned a long time ago.

I was just about to close my diary and go to sleep when the following thought popped into my head. Charon obviously didn't stay over in Marathon by chance. It's terrible to think of, but it seems I have guessed what the matter is. Did they really decide on such a step? I remember now all that rabble under my roof, those strange friends of his with their vulgar habits and uncouth manners. Some kind of mechanics with rough voices, drinking whiskey without seltzer and smoking revolting cheap cigarettes. Short-haired loudmouths with sickly complexions, parading about in jeans and colored shirts, never wiping their feet in the hallway; and all those conversations about world government, about some kind of technocracy, about those unthinkable "isms"; and their organic hostility to everything that brings peace and security to a quiet man. I remember it all now, and I understand what has happened. Yes, my son-in-law and his confederates are radicals, and so they acted. All those conversations about Martians - they're merely distorted echoes of the true facts. Conspirators have always loved bold and mysterious-sounding names, so it's not impossible that they now call themselves "The Martians," or something like "Society for the Preservation of the Planet Mars," or let's say "The Martian Renaissance." The fact that the M.A. of agriculture bears the name of Marsyas strikes me as most significant: he's most likely the ringleader of the coup. What I still can't understand is why the putschists dislike wheat and have such a ridiculous interest in stomach juice. Probably this is a diversionary tactic to confound public opinion.

Of course, I'm no good at interpreting putsches and revolutions, I find it difficult to explain everything that is going on, but I know one thing. When they drove us like sheep to freeze in the trenches, when the blackshirts pawed our women on our own beds, where were you then, Messrs. Radicals? You also put on the colors and shouted: "Long live the leader!" If you like revolutions so much, why do you always make them at the wrong time? Who needs you and your overthrows now? Me? Or Mvrtilus? Or mavbe Achilles? Why don't you leave us alone? All of you, gentlemen, are noncommissioned officers, and no better than that fool patriot Polyphemus.

This eczema, blast it, is driving me crazy. I'm scratching like a monkey at a fair, no drops will help it, no salves. All the druggists are liars. I don't need any medicines. I need peace and quiet, that's what!

If Charon has enough brains not to remain in the back lines, I've got the first class made.

June 5

I slept poorly last night. First Artemis woke me up when she came in at 1 a.m. I firmly decided to make a clean breast of it with her, but nothing came of it: she kissed me and locked herself in her bedroom. I had to take a soporific to calm down. Began to snooze, dreamed some sort of nonsense. At 4 a.m. I was again awakened, this time by Charon. Everyone is sleeping, but he goes on talking loudly throughout the house, as if no one else were here. I threw on my robe and went out into the living room. Lord, he was a terrible sight. I understood at once that the overthrow had not succeeded.

He sat at the table greedily eating everything that drowsy Artemis was serving him, and on the table, right on the tablecloth, were lying the greasy dismantled parts of some kind of firearm. He was unshaven, his eyes were red and inflamed, his hair was disheveled and stuck out in matted clumps. He munched his food like a honey-dipper. He had no jacket on, so it must be assumed he came home in precisely that appearance. Nothing of the chief editor of a small but respectable newspaper remained in him. His shirt was torn and smeared with dirt; his hands were filthy with broken fingernails, and horrible swollen scratches could be seen on his chest.

He didn't bother to greet me, simply glanced at me with crazy eyes and grumbled as he choked on the food: "You asked for it, you bastards!" I let this savage remark pass by my ears, because I saw the man was not in his right mind, but my heart sank and my legs felt so weak that I had to sit down on the couch. Artemis, too, was awfully scared, though she tried every which way to hide it. But Charon paid no attention to her and just barked for all the neighborhood to hear: "Bread!" Or: "Brandy, damn it!" Or: "Where's the mustard, Arta? I've asked for it twenty times already."

We had no conversation in the usual sense of the word. Trying in vain to overcome my palpitations, I asked him how he had ridden here. In answer he roared completely unintelligibly that he had ridden on somebody's back, but not the person he should have ridden. I tried to change the subject, to direct the conversation along more peaceful channels, and inquired about the weather in Marathon. He looked at me as if I had mortally insulted him and simply roared in his plate: "Brainless idiots ..." It was quite impossible to talk with him. Every other word was a curse, both while he was eating and afterwards, when he pushed the plates away with his elbow and began to assemble his weapon with renewed vigor. It's a good thing Hermione sleeps so soundly, so she wasn't present for this scene: she can't stand vulgarity. Everyone was a bastard to him; I just couldn't understand what had happened.

Here's the way it went: "All those bastards have become such worthless bastards that now any miserable bastard can do what he likes with the bastards, and not a single bastard will raise a finger to stop the bastards from handing us any old crap."

Poor Artemis stood behind his back wringing her fingers, and the tears ran down her cheeks. From time to time she glanced at me imploringly, but what could I do? I needed help myself; the nervous tension had practically blindfolded me. Without leaving off cursing for a moment, he assembled his weapon (it turned out to be a modern machine gun), inserted the cartridge and rose heavily to his feet, knocking two plates on the floor. Artemis, my poor daughter, her pale face drained of the last drop of blood, leaned over to him, and then, it seemed, he softened up a bit.

"There, there, kid," he said, dropping the cursing and hugging her awkwardly around the shoulders. "I could have taken you with me, but it wouldn't have been much fun for you. I know you like the back of my hand."

Even I felt the painful necessity for Artemis to find the right words at this moment. And, as if catching my telepathic thought, the girl gushed with tears and asked him, in my opinion, the main question: "What will happen to us now?"

I understood at once that, from Charon's point of view, these were not really the right words. He tucked his machine gun under his arm, slapped Artemis on the fanny, and said with a mean grin: "Don't worry, kiddie, nothing new will happen to you." After this he headed straight out. But I couldn't permit him to leave like that, without giving us any explanations.

"Just a minute, Charon," I said, overcoming my weakness. "What will happen now? What will they do to us?"

This question of mine drove him into an indescribable fury. He stopped on the threshold, turned half around and, knocking his knee painfully, hissed through his teeth these strange words: "If only one bastard would ask what he should do. But no, every bastard asks only what they will do to him. Rest easy, yours shall be the heavenly kingdom on Earth."

After this he went out, loudly slamming the door, and a minute later his car was heard roaring down the street.

The next hour was pure hell. Artemis had an attack of something like hysterics, though it more resembled uncontrollable rage. She broke all the dishes left on the table, yanked off the tablecloth and hurled it at the television set, banged on the door with her fists and shouted something in a choked voice that sounded like this: "So to you I'm a fool? ... I'm a fool to you, huh? ... And what are you? ... What are you? ... I spit on the whole deal.... You do what you want, and I'll do what I want! ... Got it? ... Got it? ... Got it?... You'll come running, you'll come begging on your knees!..."

Probably I should have given her some water, slapped her cheeks and the rest, but I myself was laid out on the couch, and there was no one to bring me a validus pill. It ended with Artemis dashing off to her room without paying any attention to me and with me, after resting a bit, crawling off to bed and falling into some sort of half-faint.

Morning came, overcast and rainy. (Temperature: +17° C, cloud cover: 10, no wind.) Fortunately I had slept through Artemis's explanation to Hermione of the mess in the living room. I only know that there had been a scene and both were now puffed up with anger. While she served the coffee, Hermione looked at me with the obvious intention of drawing me into the conversation, but she kept quiet. Most likely I looked pretty bad, and she's a kind woman, which is why I value her. After coffee, I was gathering strength to go to The Five Spot when a messenger boy arrived with a supposed piece of news signed by Polyphemus. It turns out I am a rank-and-file member of the city's "Voluntary Anti-Martian Patrol" and am already instructed to "appear at 10 a.m. on Harmony Square with firearms or sidearms and a three-day food supply." What does he think I am, a babe in the woods? Of course, I didn't go anywhere, purely on principle. From Myrtilus, who is still living in his tent, I found out that the farmers have been coming to the mayor's office since dawn; they are receiving sacks of the new grain-seeds and taking them back to their fields. Supposedly the wheat harvest, consigned to destruction, is being bought up before cutting by the government at a good price, and advances on the harvest of new grain are being offered. In all of this the farmers suspect the usual agrarian rigamarole, but since no money has been demanded of them, nor written contracts, they don't know what to think. Myrtilus assures me (!) that there are no Martians, because life is impossible on Mars. There is simply a new agrarian policy. Nevertheless, he is ready at any moment to leave the city, and, just in case, he also took a bag of seeds. In the papers, the same as yesterday, there is nothing but wheat and gastric juice. If it keeps on like this, Fm going to cancel my subscription. On the radio - also wheat and gastric juice. I don't even turn it on anymore, I just watch television, where everything is as it was before the putsch. Mr. Nicostratus drove up in his car, Artemis skipped out to him and they drove away. I don't want to think about it. Maybe, in the final analysis, it's fate.

Since all this babbling about wheat and gastric juice hasn't stopped, the putsch has apparently succeeded after all. Charon, due to his usual unsociability, didn't get what he'd counted on, argued with everyone there and found himself in the opposition. I'm afraid that because of him things will be unpleasant for us. When madmen like Charon take up a machine gun, they fire it. My God, will the time ever come when things are not unpleasant for me?

June 6

Temperature: +16° C, cloud cover: 10, wind from the southwest at 6 meters per second. Fixed my wind gauge.

The eczema is driving me crazy. I'll have to bandage up my hands. Besides that, my frozen ears are aching - probably from the change in the weather.

Martians are Martians. I'm sick of arguing about it.

June 7

My eye still hurts. It's all swollen up and I can't see anything out of it. Good thing it's the left eye. Achilles' eyewash only helps a little bit. Achilles says the shiner will be noticeable for no more than a week. Right now it's reddish blue, later it will turn green, then get yellow and disappear completely. Still, what a cruel and uncouth thing to do! To strike an elderly man who was only trying to ask an innocent question. If this is the way the Martians will start, I hate to think how they will end. And there's no one to complain to, I can only wait until the matter is cleared up. My eye hurts so much that it's terrible to remember how pleased I was with the peaceful morning today. (Temperature: +20° C, cloud cover: 0, wind from the south at 1 meter per second.)

When I went up to the attic after breakfast to make some meteorological observations, I noticed with some surprise that the fields beyond the city had acquired a definite bluish tinge. Farther off, the fields blended in so completely with the color of the sky that the line of the horizon was completely effaced, even though visibility was excellent and there was no smoke whatsoever. These new Martian seeds have sprouted up remarkably fast. It's to be expected that in a day or so they will wipe out the wheat altogether,

Arriving at the square, I found that almost all the boys, as well as a huge number of other townspeople, who should have been at work, not to mention farmers and schoolchildren who should have been playing games, were crowding around three large vans painted over with colorful posters and advertisements. I thought at first that this was a traveling circus, especially since the advertisements proclaimed incomparable tight-wire walkers and the other usual heroes of the arena, but Morpheus, who had been standing there a long time, explained to me that this was no circus, but a mobile donor station. Inside were installed special suction pumps with hoses, and next to every pump there sat a big husky guy in a doctor's uniform who offered to draw off the excesses of everybody who entered and to give a remarkable price: five bills per glass.

"What kind of excesses?" I asked. It turned out to be excesses of stomach juice. The whole world is founded on stomach juice. "Are they really Martians?" I asked.

"What do you mean, Martians?" asked Morpheus. "They're big husky hairy guys. That fellow has one eye."

"So what if he does?" I naturally objected. "A member of any race, be he on Earth or on Mars, has one eye, if the other one is injured."

I didn't realize then that these words of mine would prove prophetic. I was simply irritated by Morpheus's presumptuous attitude.

"I've never heard of one-eyed Martians in my life," he declared.

The people around us were listening to our conversation, and so he, in an attack of vanity, deemed it necessary to maintain his dubious reputation as a debater. But he still doesn't know what he's talking about.

"These are no Martians," he states. "Just ordinary guys from the suburbs. You can find a dozen like them in every tavern.''

"Our information about Mars is so scanty," I say calmly, "that to propose that Martians are like ordinary guys in suburban taverns at least doesn't contradict any scientific truth."

"You said it," puts in an unknown farmer standing by. "You said that very convincingly, Mr. What's-Your-Name. The one-eyed guy has his arms tattooed up to his elbows, full of naked women. The way he rolled up his sleeves and the way he came over to me with that hose - no, I thought, we don't need any of this."

"So what does science have to say about tattooing on the Martians?" Morpheus asked spitefully. He wanted to stick me with that one. A cheap trick, it smells of the barber in him. You can't beat me with stunts like that.

"Professor Zephyrus," said I, looking him straight in the eye, "the chief astronomer of the Marathonian observatory, has never denied in any one of his numerous articles such a practice among the Martians."

"That's right," confirmed the farmer. "Professors wear glasses, they see more."

And Morpheus had to swallow all that. He piped down and made his way out of the crowd, saying, "Time for a beer." I stayed to see what would happen next.

For a while nothing happened. Everyone just stood around, staring and talking quietly to one another. Farmers and merchants - they're an indecisive folk. Then a movement occurred in the first rows. Some villager suddenly whipped off his straw hat, stomped on it with all his might and cried out loudly: "Heh! Five bills - that's money too, isn't it?" Uttering these words, he walked decisively up the wooden steps and thrust himself in the door of the van, so that all we could see was the back of his body, all dusty and covered with burrs. What he was saying and what he was asking could not be heard because of the distance. I saw only that at first his stance was stiff, then he sort of went soft, began to shift his weight, stuck his hands in his pockets and backed out, shaking his head. Then, without looking at anyone, he gingerly stepped down to the ground, picked up his hat and, thoroughly knocking the dust off of it, rejoined the crowd.

In the door of the van there appeared a man who was indeed very tall and indeed blind in one eye. If it hadn't been for his white uniform, he would certainly have passed for an inhabitant of some thieves' den, what with the black string of his eye patch across his face, his unshaven stubble and his hairy tattooed arms. Looking us over darkly, he rolled down his sleeves, pulled out a cigarette and, after lighting up, said in a rough voice: " Well, come on! It's worth five bills. Five bills for every little glass. That's real money! On the spot. How much drudging do you have to do for five smackers? But here all you have to do is swallow a hose, and it's over in no time. Well?"

I looked at him and couldn't help but wonder at the shortsightedness of the administration. How could they expect a townsman, or even a farmer, to entrust his organism to such a loud-mouthed thug? I made my way out of the crowd and went over to The Five Spot.

All of the boys were already there, every one of them with his fowling piece, and some of them with white bands around their sleeves. Polyphemus had pulled on his old army cap, and, drenched with sweat, he delivered a speech. According to him, the evil deeds of the Martians had already become unbearable and all patriots were moaning and sweating blood under their yoke and the time had finally come to give them a decisive rebuff. And the ones responsible for it all, Polyphemus asserted, were the deserters and traitors such as those fat-assed, gobbling generals, the druggist Achilles, the coward Myrtilus and that backslider Apollo.

My eyes clouded over when I heard these last words. I completely lost the gift of speech and recovered myself only when I noticed that no one but myself was listening to Polyphemus. All of them, it turned out, were listening not to the one-legged stooge, but to Silenus, who had just returned from the mayor's office and was relating that from now on all the taxes would be levied exclusively in stomach juice and that an order had come from Marathon converting stomach juice into the usual units of money. Supposedly stomach juice would now be transferable, and all banks and savings trusts were ready to change it into cash.

"How can that be?" said Dymus. "I don't understand. What are we going to do, carry some sort of container instead of wallets? And what if I bring them water instead of juice?"

"Listen, Silenus," said Morpheus, "I owe you a tenner. Will you take juice?" He got very excited, since he always lacks money for drinks and has always drunk at another's expense. "Good times are here, buddies!" he exclaimed. "For example, if I feel like a drink, I just go to the bank, discharge my excesses for them and get cash in exchange. Then - off to the tavern!"

Here Polyphemus began to shout again. "They've bought you out!" he shouted. "You've sold yourself to the Martians for stomach juice! Here you've sold yourselves out, and they drive around like they were on their own Mars!"

And at that moment there came across the square, slowly and noiselessly, a very strange black car, which seemed to have no wheels, no windows and no doors. Children were running behind it yelling and whistling; some of them tried to catch hold of it from the back, but it was completely smooth, like a piano, and there was nothing for them to hold onto. A very unusual car.

"Could it really belong to the Martians?" I asked.

"Who else?" said Polyphemus irritably. "Is it yours?"

"No one's saying it's mine," I objected. "There are all sorts of cars in the world. Do they all have to belong to the Martians?"

"I'm not saying they all belong to the Martians, you old hunk of dung!" Polyphemus roared. "I'm saying the Martians are riding around town as if they were at home, the bastards! And all of you here have sold yourselves out."

I only shrugged my shoulders, not wanting to get involved, but Silenus answered him very thoughtfully: "Excuse me, Polyphemus, but your shouting is beginning to wear on me. And not only me. In my opinion, we have all fulfilled our duty. We enlisted in the volunteer squad and we cleaned our weapons - what more do you want, if you don't mind me asking?"

"Patrols! Patrols are needed!" said Polyphemus, choking with emotion. "To cut off the roads! To keep the Martians out of the city!"

"But how are you going to keep them out?"

"Blast you, Silenus! How can you keep them out? Very simple! Halt, who goes? Halt or I'll fire! You asked for it, bang!"

I couldn't stand this. He's not a man, he's a gung-ho.

"Well, maybe we could form patrols," said Dymus. "It's not too hard for us, is it?"

"It's not our job," I said decisively. "Silenus here will tell you that it's against the law. That's the army's job. Let the army worry about patrols and whatever shooting has to be done."

I can't stand these military games, especially when Polyphemus is in command. Some kind of sadism. I remember once when we had civil-defense training in the city in the event of a nuclear attack, and he went around throwing smoke bombs to create a realistic effect, so no one would go without his gas mask. How many people were asphyxiated - well, it's simply a nightmare. He's a noncommissioned officer, you can't trust him with anything. Or the time he barged into the gym class at school, chewed out the instructor in the most vulgar language and took it upon himself to show the kiddies how to march in step. If they put him on patrol, he'd fire his shotgun at everyone until they stopped bringing goods into the city. He'd lash out at the Martians, and they, most likely, would burn the whole city down in retaliation. But our old-timers are like children, honest to God. Patrol they want, patrol they'll get. I spat for all to see and went off to the mayor's office.

Mr. Nicostratus was polishing his nails. He answered my hesitant questions more or less as follows. The government's financial policies will change somewhat under the new conditions. A large role in monetary matters will now be played by the so-called stomach juice. It may be expected that in the near future the aforementioned juice will begin to have the same currency as money. So far there have been no special instructions about pensions, but there are substantial grounds for assuming that once taxes are levied in the so-called stomach juice, pensions will be paid out in the same so-called stomach juice. My heart sank, but I collected myself and asked Mr. Nicostratus directly if it wasn't possible to understand his words to mean that the so-called stomach juice was not actually stomach juice, but some sort of symbol of the new financial policy. Mr. Nicostratus shrugged his shoulders indefinitely and, continuing to examine his fingernails, stated, "Stomach juice, Mr. Apollo, is stomach juice."

"What good is stomach juice to me?" I asked in complete desperation.

He shrugged his shoulders a second time and remarked, "You know perfectly well that every person needs stomach juice."

It was absolutely clear to me that Mr. Nicostratus was either lying or holding something back. I was so desperate that I requested an audience with Mr. Mayor. But I was refused. Then I left the mayor's office and signed up for the patrol.

If a man who has worked flawlessly for thirty years in the fallow field of public education is offered a vial of stomach juice, this man has the right to demonstrate any degree of indignation he so desires. Whether Martians or non-Martians are responsible is beside the point. I cannot abide any anarchic activity, but I am willing to fight for my rights with a rifle in my hands. And even though everyone will know that my protest has a purely symbolic value, let them think about this, let them know that they are not dealing with some dumb animal. Of course, if the donor stations should become our system and the banks and savings trusts should accept stomach juice in exchange for cash, I would take a different stand on the matter. However, so far only Silenus has spoken about banks and savings trusts, so it's only an unconfirmed rumor. As regards the donor stations, Morpheus, after signing up for the patrol, decided to anoint the deal right away and gave himself into the hands of the one-eyed thug. He returned with teary red eyes, showed us a crisp new fiver and reported that the vans were presently leaving. That means there can be no talk about any new system: they came and they left. If you managed to donate your excesses - good for you. If you didn't - blame yourself. In my view, this is outrageous.

Polyphemus appointed me along with Calais the stutterer to patrol Harmony Square and the adjoining streets from 12 to 2 a.m. After giving us our certification made out in Silenus's hand, he slapped me on the back with great emotion and said, "The old guard! What would these crappy civvies do without us, Phoebus? I knew when we got down to brass tacks you'd be with us." We embraced and both shed tears. Actually, Polyphemus is not such a bad guy, he simply likes people to follow his orders without question. A completely understandable desire. I requested his permission for free time and headed for Achilles' place. A patrol's a patrol, but you ought to play it safe.

What sort of a thing is stomach juice? I asked Achilles. Who can benefit from it? What can it be used for? Achilles said it was necessary for the proper digestion of food and most likely nothing else. Fd known that before I'd asked him.

"Soon I will be able to offer you a large batch of the so-called stomach juice," I said. "Will you take it?"

He answered that he would think about it, and right here offered to trade his unserrated air-mail stamp of '28 for my incomplete "zoo park" series. You have to admit, the unserrated beauty is unique, but the one Achilles showed me has two strips glued together and some kind of greasy spot. I don't know, I just don't know.

Coming out of the drugstore, I saw the Martian car again. It might have been the same one, but perhaps another. Breaking all the traffic laws, it floated down the middle of the street, but with the speed of a pedestrian, so I was able to get a good look at it. I was walking to the tavern and it was going the same way. My first impression proved to be correct: the car most resembled a streamlined piano covered with dust. From time to time something underneath it flashed and the car shuddered a bit, but this was apparently not a malfunction because it continued to move steadily forward without stopping for a moment. I couldn't make out any windows or doors even from a close distance, but the absence of wheels struck me most of all. True, my build did not permit me to bend down low enough to look at the bottom. Perhaps there were wheels there after all - it couldn't be that there wasn't even a single wheel.

Suddenly the car stopped. And wouldn't you know it, it stopped right in front of Mr. Laomedon's estate. I recall that I thought bitterly: it seems there are people in the world to whom it makes no difference whether it's a new president, an old president, Martians or anybody else. Every power always pays them respect and attention, I thought, which they don't deserve; in fact they deserve the opposite. But something completely unexpected happened. Assuming with good reason that someone was going to get out of the car and that I would finally see a real live Martian, I stood to the side and watched along with the other townspeople, whose line of thinking apparently coincided with mine. To our amazement and disappointment, there emerged from the car not Martians, but some kind of proper young men in tight coats and identical berets. Three of them went to the grand front entrance, while two of them stayed with the car, sticking their hands deep in their pockets and leaning casually on the car with various parts of their bodies. The front door opened, the three entered and immediately strange but not very loud noises were heard, as if someone were trying to move the furniture around by himself and others were beating a carpet with regular blows. The two standing by the car paid no attention to these sounds. They kept their same positions, one looking carelessly down the street, the other yawning and glancing at the top floor of the estate. They also didn't change their positions when a minute later the front door opened slowly and my insulter, Mr. Laomedon's chauffeur, came out cautiously, like a blind man. His face was pale, his mouth hanging open, his eyes bulging and glassy, and both his hands were pressed to his stomach. Coming out onto the sidewalk, he walked a few paces, dropped with a groan, sat for a while bending over farther and farther, and then toppled over on his side, curled up, kicked his legs and froze stock still. I must confess that at first I understood nothing. Everything proceeded so leisurely, in such a calm businesslike manner, against the background of the usual city noise, that the feeling arose and stuck with me that this was the way it should be. I did not experience any anxiety and did not seek any explanations. I felt such trust in those young men - so proper, so restrained.... Now one of them distractedly glanced at the chauffeur lying there, lit up a cigarette and again began to examine the top floor. It even seemed to me that he was smiling. Then a stamping of feet was heard, and one after another there came out of the entrance the young man in the tight coat, wiping his lips with a handkerchief; Mr. Laomedon in a splendid eastern robe, without a hat and in handcuffs; another young man in a tight coat, taking his gloves off on the way; and finally a third young man in a tight coat, loaded with weapons. With his right hand he held three or four machine guns to his chest, and in the left he carried several pistols, dangling the trigger loops on his fingers, and besides these a tommy gun hung from each shoulder. I glanced at Mr. Laomedon only once, but this was enough for me: I can still see something red, wet and sticky. The whole cavalcade crossed the street leisurely and disappeared into the inner recesses of the car. The two young men remaining outside lazily pushed off from the polished side, walked over to the prostrate chauffeur, carefully took him by the hands and feet and, swaying him slightly, tossed him into the house. One of them then drew a piece of paper out of his pocket and neatly stuck it next to the doorbell, after which the car, without turning around, moved with its former speed in the opposite direction, and the two young men with the most unassuming faces walked through the parting crowd and disappeared around the corner.

When I came out of the stupor into which the unexpectedness and unusualness of this occurrence had thrown me and again recovered the ability to think, I felt something like a psychic shock, as if a turning point in history had been reached right before my eyes. I am sure that the other witnesses experienced and felt something similar. We all crowded in front of the entrance, but no one resolved to go inside. I put on my glasses and over the heads of the crowd read the proclamation stuck below the doorbell.

It read:

Narcotics are a poison and the disgrace of the nation! The time has come to make an end of narcotics. And we shall make an end of them, and you will help us. We shall punish unmercifully those who spread narcotics.

If it had been anyone else, there would have been enough to talk about for two hours or more, but this time everyone only exchanged interjections, not having the strength to fight against their initial timidity: "Aiee-aiee-aiee.... Better do it!... Ehe-he-he.... Egads! Oh, no!"

Someone had called the police and a doctor. The doctor went into the house and attended to the chauffeur. Then Pandareus arrived in the police buggy. He stomped around on the porch, read the proclamation several times, scratched the back of his head and even peeked in the door, but was afraid to go inside, even though the doctor was calling him irritably in the most disrespectful language. He stood in the doorway, spreading his legs, sticking his palms under his strap and puffing up like a turkey.

With the appearance of the police the crowd grew somewhat bolder and began to speak out more definitely:

"So that's the way they do it, huh?"

"Yeah, that's the way, it seems...."

"Interesting, interesting, isn't it, gentlemen?"

"I never would have believed it."

I sensed with alarm that the tongues were becoming untied and decided to leave, although I was eaten up with curiosity, but here Silenus turned to Pandareus with a direct question: "So, Pan, did the law triumph after all? Is this what you finally decided?"

Pandareus pursed his lips significantly and, hesitating a bit, stated, "I assume this was not our decision."

"What do you mean, not yours? Whose, then?"

"I suppose, the gendarmerie in the capital," declared Polyphemus in a thunderous whisper, glancing around on all sides.

"What kind of gendarmerie is that?" people in the crowd objected. "Suddenly the gendarmerie is riding around in a Martian car! No, that's no gendarmerie."

"So what's your opinion, huh? Were they really Martians?"

Polyphemus puffed up even more and bawled: "Hey, who's that talking about Martians? Watch out!"

But they paid no more attention to him. The tongues came completely unhinged: "The car might be Martian, but they themselves are not Martians, that's for sure. Their ways are the same as ours, human."

"Right! What do Martians care about narcotics, I'd like to know."

"Hey, you old-timers, a new broom sweeps clean. But what business of theirs is our stomach juice?"

"No, gentlemen, those were no people. Too calm, you see, too quiet. I think they were Martians. They work like machines."

"Right, machines! Robots! Why should the Martians dirty their hands? They have robots."

Pandareus, unable to hold back, also joined in the guessing game. "No, old fellows," he declared, "they're not robots. That's just the system now. They take only deaf-and-dumb men into the gendarmerie. For reasons of state security."

This hypothesis at first caused confusion, but then brought poisonous retorts, very witty for the most part. I recall only the remark of grouchy Paralus. He delivered himself of the opinion that it wouldn't be a bad thing if the police took only deaf-and-dumb men, only not for reasons of state security, but to protect innocent people from all the rubbish dumped on them by official spokesmen. Polyphemus, who earlier had unbuttoned his jacket, now puffed up, buttoned up again and hollered: "You've had your say - that's all!"

And so we unfortunately had to disperse, although at just that moment the ambulance pulled up. The old horse's ass flew into such a fury that we could only observe from afar how they carried the injured chauffeur out of the entrance-way and afterwards, to our surprise, the bodies of two others. We still don't know who these two were.

All of the boys headed for the tavern, and me too. Those same two young men were standing casually at the bar. As before, they were calm and quiet, they drank gin and looked distractedly over the heads. I ordered myself a complete meal and, eating my fill, watched how the most curious of our group gradually moved closer to the young men. It was fun to watch how ineptly Morpheus tried to start a conversation with them about the weather in Marathon, and Paralus, intending to take the bull by the horns, offered them a drink. The young men, as if seeing no one around them, briskly gulped down the drinks pushed toward them, but maintained an impartial silence. Jokes didn't amuse them, they didn't catch hints and seemed to miss direct questions altogether. I didn't know what to think. I was so taken with their exceptional restraint, their complete indifference to the amusing attempts to draw them into conversation, that I began to incline to the thought that they were indeed Martian robots, that the repulsive appearance of the Martians prevented them from openly showing their true faces. Then I suspected that they were the Martians themselves, about whom we still know nothing, when you get right down to it. The boys, giving themselves away completely, clustered about the young men and made remarks about them without any restraint; some even dared to try touching their coats. All were now convinced that these were robots before them.

Iapetus even began to worry. Serving me brandy, he said nervously, "How can they be robots? They've each had two gins, two brandies, two packs of cigarettes, and who's going to pay?"

I explained to him that the robot's program would have accounted for drinks and cigarettes and therefore would certainly account for some means of payment. Iapetus calmed down, but at this moment a fight started at the bar.

As we learned later, grouchy Paralus had made a bet with that fool Dymus that Dymus could touch a burning cigarette to the robot's hand and nothing would happen. Here is what I saw with my own eyes. From the crowd of people enjoying themselves Dymus suddenly burst like a cork from a bottle. He flew backwards all the way across the room, pumping his feet in tiny circles and knocking down tables and people in his path until he dropped in a corner. Not a second passed before Paralus, in exactly the same manner, found himself in another corner. The boys flung themselves in all directions, and I, without understanding a thing, saw the young men sitting quietly at the bar as before, thoughtfully raising the glasses of alcohol to their lips with identical movements.

Paralus and Dymus were picked up and dragged behind the curtains to be revived. I took my glass and also went behind the curtains. I wanted to find out what had happened. I arrived just as Dymus came around and sat there with the most idiotic expression on his face, feeling his chest. Paralus had not yet recovered consciousness, but was already gulping gin and washing it down with soda. The waitress was standing beside him with a towel ready to bandage up his chin when he came to. Here I learned the version of the incident just described and agreed with the rest that Paralus was a provocateur and Dymus was simply a fool no better than Pandareus.

However, having expressed these reasoned considerations, the boys were by no means satisfied, but took it into their heads to do something about it. Polyphemus, who had kept in the shade up to this point, announced that this would be the first military action of our voluntary patrol. We'd jump the hoodlums when they came out of the tavern, he said, and he began to order who should stand where and when we would attack. I immediately disassociated myself from this venture. First of all, I am an opponent of violence, there's nothing of the noncommissioned officer in me. Second, I didn't see that the young men had been in the wrong. And finally, I planned not to fight with them, but rather to have a talk with them about my own affairs. I quietly came out from behind the curtains, returned to my table and by these very movements initiated another occurrence, one very bitter for me.

But even now, when I look over the events of the day with completely different eyes, I must state that the logic of my actions was and remains faultless. The young men were not from our area, I reasoned. The fact that they had arrived in the Martian car indicated that they most likely came from the capital. Moreover, their participation in the arrest of Mr. Laomedon proved without a doubt that they belonged to the new regime: they would hardly have sent some minor agents against Mr. Laomedon. Therefore, it followed from the logic of things that these young men must certainly be well informed about the new conditions; they would be able to tell me things of interest. Being in the position of a little man who was ridiculed by Mr. Laomedon's chauffeur and refused information by Mr. Mayor's secretary, I couldn't pass up this opportunity to get some true facts. On the other hand, the young men did not raise any fears in me. The fact that they had handled Mr. Laomedon and his bodyguards rather brutally did not alarm me at all. It was their duty and Mr. Laomedon had deserved a good hiding for a long time. As regards the incident with Paralus and Dymus, well, my friends, Dymus is an idiot, it's impossible to deal with him, and Paralus is able to bring out anyone's worst side with his grouchy wisecracks. I won't even mention the fact that I myself would not allow anyone to call me a robot, let alone stick a cigarette on my hand.

Consequently, when I had finished my brandy, I went over to the young men, completely confident of the success of my undertaking. I had thought out the plan of the impending conversation in all its details, having taken into consideration the nature of their occupation, their mood immediately after the incident and their evidently innate taciturnity and restraint. I had intended at first to ask their forgiveness for the thoughtless behavior of my compatriots. Further, I would introduce myself, express the hope that I was not bothering them with my conversation, complain about the quality of the brandy, which lapetus frequently dilutes with cheaper sorts, and offer to treat them from my personal bottle. And only after this and after we had discussed the weather in Marathon and in our town, did I intend very lightly and delicately to pass to the main question. Approaching them, I noticed that one of them was busy smoking his cigarette, while the other, turning away from the bar, observed my approach intently and with some interest, as it seemed to me. I decided therefore to address him directly.

Coming up, I doffed my hat and said, "Good evening." And then this hoodlum made a sort of lazy movement with his shoulder and it suddenly seemed as if a hand grenade had exploded inside of my head. I don't remember anything. I recall only that I was lying for a long time next to Paralus behind the curtains, glugging gin, washing it down with soda, and someone was applying a cold wet napkin to my wounded eye.

And now I ask myself: What more can you expect? No one interceded for me, no one raised a voice of protest. Everything repeats itself. Hoodlums are again spreading terror, beating up citizens in the streets. And when Polyphemus drove me home in his miniature car, my daughter, as unconcerned as everyone else, was kissing Mr. Secretary in the garden. No, even if I had known how it would all turn out, I still had a duty, an obligation to try to engage them in conversation. I would have been more careful, I wouldn't have approached them, but from whom else can I find out anything? I don't want to worry over every copper, I can't force myself to teach anymore, I don't want to sell the house in which I have lived for so many years. This is what I fear, and I want peace and quiet.

June 8

Temperature: +17° C, cloud cover: 8, wind from the south at 3 meters per second. I'm sitting at home, not going out, not seeing anybody. The swelling has gone down and the injured spot almost doesn't hurt, but it still looks terrible. All day I examined my stamps and watched television. Everything is the same in town. Last night our golden youth besieged Madam Persephone's house, which was loaded with soldiers. They say it was a real free-for-all. The field of battle was held by the army. (They're no Martians, you can be sure of that.) Nothing special in the newspapers. Not a word about the embargo; you get the impression it's been called off entirely. There's a strange address by the war minister, set in brevier type, which says that our membership in the Military Commonwealth represents a burden for the country and is not so well founded as might appear at first sight. Thank God, they've finally figured it out after eleven years! But most of all they are writing about a farmer named Periphas who is remarkable in that he can give up to four litres of stomach juice a day without any harm to his organism. His hard life is reported with many intimate details. Interviews with him are recorded and scenes from his biography are acted out on television. A sturdy, rather crude man of forty-five years, without a grain of intellect. You look at him and never suspect that you are looking at such an amazing phenomenon. He kept insisting it was his habit of sucking a piece of sugar every morning. I'll have to try it.

Yes! In our papers there is an article by Calais the veterinarian about the danger of narcotics. There Calais writes that the regular use of narcotics by large-horned cattle is exceptionally harmful to the production of stomach juice. A diagram is even attached. An interesting observation: everything is printed black on white in Calais's article, yet it's unbearably difficult to read. It seems as if he were writing and still stuttering. However, it turns out that Mr. Laomedon was exterminated because he prevented the citizens from freely drawing off their stomach juice. One gets the impression that stomach juice is the foundation stone of the new governmental policy. Such a thing has never occurred before. But then, when you think about it, why not?

Hermione returned from a visit to friends and related that in the former estate of Mr. Laomedon a permanent donor station for the collection of stomach juice was being set up. If this is true, then I approve and support it. I always stand for permanence and stability.

Ah, my stamps, my little stampies! You alone never upset me!

June 9

Temperature: +16° C, cloud cover: 5, a slight rain. The swelling has completely vanished; however, as Achilles predicted, the whole area around the eye has taken on a hideous greenish tinge. I can't show myself on the street: you wouldn't hear anything but stupid jokes. This morning I phoned the mayor's office, but Mr. Nicostratus was pleased to be in a humorous mood and did not communicate anything new to me regarding my pension. Of course, I became very upset, tried to calm myself with my stamps, but even the stamps did not console me. Then I sent Hermione to the drugstore for tranquilizers, but she returned with empty hands. It turned out that Achilles had received a special notice instructing him to distribute tranquilizers only by prescription of the city physician. I flew into a fury and phoned Achilles, started up an argument, but to tell the truth - what could I expect from him? All medicines containing narcotics are under the strict supervision of the police and specially appointed people from the mayor's office. What can you do: if you cut down a forest, the chips will fly. I got my cognac and took a drink, right in front of Hermione.

It helped. I even feel better. And Hermione didn't let out a peep.

This morning Myrtilus's family returned, even though he is still living in his tent. To be honest, I was glad. This was the first sign that the situation in the country was becoming stable. But then suddenly after lunch I saw Myrtilus putting them all on the bus again. What was the matter?

"Sure, sure," Myrtilus answered me in his usual manner. "You're all such wise guys, and I'm a fool...."

It seems he had gone to The Five Spot and learned that the Martians intended to call the comptroller and architect to account for their machinations and squandering of funds; supposedly they had already summoned them somewhere. I tried to explain to Myrtilus that this was a good thing, it was fair. But where would it lead!

"Sure, sure," he answered. "It's fair.... Today the comptroller and architect, tomorrow the mayor, and the day after tomorrow I don't know who, maybe me. Nothing doing. Look at you - they hung a black eye on you, was that fair?"

I can't talk with him, he can go .. .

A Mr. Corybantus phoned. It turns out he is replacing Charon at the newspaper. A pitiful, trembling voice; the paper must be having difficulties with the authorities. He begged me to tell him if Charon would be returning soon. I spoke very sympathetically with him, of course, but I didn't say a word about Charon having already returned once. Intuitively I feel it isn't worth spreading around. God knows where Charon is now and what he's doing. That's all I need: unpleasantries over politics. I don't talk to anyone about him, and I've forbidden Artemis and Hermione as well. Hermione understood me at once, but Artemis had to make a scene.

June 10

Only now have I recovered somewhat, though I am as sick and distraught as before. The eczema has spread as never before. Fm covered all over with blisters and keep scratching, though I know I shouldn't. And terrifying phantoms pursue me without a letup; I try to get away from them, but can't. I understand: take up arms and kill, kill or be killed. It's vile and disgusting, but in the final analysis it's natural. Still, no one is forcing them. Partisans! I certainly know what it's all about. But how could I know that in my declining years I would live to see it all over again?

It began yesterday morning.* Contrary to all expectations, I received a very friendly response from General Alcimus. He wrote that he remembers me well, regards me highly and wishes me all sorts of successes. This letter greatly excited me. I simply didn't know what to do with myself. I talked it over with Hermione, and she was forced to agree that I shouldn't let such a chance slip by. Only one thing worried us - the troubled times. At this point we saw Myrtilus breaking his temporary camp and beginning to carry his things back into the house. That was the last straw. Hermione made me a very elegant black patch for my wounded eye, I took my portfolio with documents, got in my automobile and set off for Marathon.

* From what follows, it appears that Mr. Apollo is writing on the morning of the eleventh about the events of the tenth. (Editor's note.)

The weather favored me. I drove peacefully along the deserted highway between fields which were turning blue and thought over the various courses of action available to me. However, as always, something unforeseen soon happened. About 40 kilometers from town the motor began to sneeze, the car started to shudder and then it stopped altogether. It happened at the top of a rise, and when I got out on the road the peaceful country landscape spread out before me, looking rather unusual, to be sure, what with the blueness of the ripening grains. I recall that I was completely calm in spite of the delay and did not restrain myself from admiring the neat white farms scattered in the distance. The blue grains stood very high, attaining the height of a man in some places. Never before had such abundant crops grown up in our parts. The highway, straight as an arrow, could be seen to the very horizon.

I lifted the hood and looked at the motor for a while, hoping to find the malfunction. But I am such a poor mechanic that in a short while I had to give up, straighten out my aching back and look around for help. However, the nearest farm was still rather far off, and on the road only one car could be seen approaching from the direction of Marathon at a rather great speed. At first I rejoiced, but soon, to my great chagrin, I became certain that it was one of the black Martian cars. Still, I did not completely lose hope, since I remembered that ordinary people might also be inside Martian cars. The prospect of hailing that grim black car did not appeal to me too much; I was still afraid there might be Martians inside, for whom I felt an instinctive aversion. But what else was there for me to do? I held my hand out across the highway and took a few steps toward the car, which was already approaching the foot of the rise. And then something horrible happened.

The car was 50 meters from me when suddenly a yellow light flashed; the car jumped and reared up like a horse. A thunderous blast reverberated, and the highway was wrapped in a cloud of smoke. Then I saw the car apparently trying to fly; it just about cleared the cloud, listing badly on its side, when one after the other two more lights flashed right beside it. The double blow tossed it over, and it crashed with its full weight on the asphalt, so hard that I could feel the tremor of the earth in my legs, now weak from this unexpected development. A terrible accident, I thought in the first moment. The car caught fire, and some kind of black figures surrounded by flames came climbing out of it. At the same moment, shooting broke out. I couldn't tell who was shooting from where, but I clearly saw who was being shot at. The black figures dashed about in the smoke and flames and fell one after the other. Through the barrage of bullets I heard heartrending inhuman cries, and then they were all stretched out next to the overturned car, which continued to burn. And even then the shooting did not stop. Then the car exploded with a horrifying boom, an unearthly white light struck me in my good eye and a thick hot gust of air whipped me about the face. I squinched involuntarily, and when I opened my eye again I saw to my horror a twisted black creature running down the highway straight toward me. It was wrapped in flames, with a tail of black soot, and looked just like a huge ape. At that moment, to the left of me, a man in a military uniform, with a machine gun at the ready, jumped out of the blue wheat, stopped in the middle of the road with his back toward me, squatted down quickly and started blasting the flaming black figure almost point blank. I was so horrified that the initial shock left me and I found sufficient strength to turn around and run at full speed to my car. Like a madman I turned the ignition, unable to see anything in front of me, forgetting that the motor wouldn't work; and then my strength again deserted me, and I remained sitting in the car, senselessly staring ahead, a passive and dumbfounded witness of a horrible tragedy. Indifference overcame me. As if in a dream, I saw armed men come out one after the other onto the highway, surround the scene of the catastrophe, bend over the burning bodies, turn them over and shout brief exchanges, barely audible for the blood pounding in my temples. Four of them gathered at the foot of the rise, and the man in the military uniform - an officer, judging by his epaulets - stood in his former place, several steps from the last victim and reloaded his gun. Then I saw him approach the prostrate figure without haste, tilt the muzzle of the gun and give a short burst. The figure shuddered repulsively and I threw up on the steering wheel and my pants. But after this the worst thing of all happened.

The officer quickly surveyed the sky, then turned toward me, looked - I will never forget that cold merciless glance - and, holding his machine gun by the strap, headed toward my car. I heard the men below shout something at him, but he didn't turn around. He headed toward me. Probably I fell unconscious for a few seconds, because I don't remember anything more until I found myself standing beside my automobile in front of the officer and two more insurgents. God, what a lot! All three were crusty and long unshaven; their clothes were ragged and splattered, and the officer's overcoat was in a disgraceful condition. The officer wore a helmet; one of the civilians, a black beret; the other one with glasses, nothing at all on his head.

"What's wrong with you, gone deaf?" said the officer sharply, shaking me by the shoulder, and the man in the beret frowned and bit out the words: "Why don't you leave him alone, what do you need to do that for?"

I gathered up the last vestiges of strength and forced myself to speak calmly, for I knew it was a matter of my life.

"What do you want?" I asked.

"An ordinary townsman," said the man in the beret. "He doesn't know anything and doesn't want to know anything!"

"Wait a minute, engineer," said the officer irritably. "Who are you?" he asked me. "What are you doing here?"

I answered all his questions without hiding anything, and while I was speaking he kept glancing around and looking at the sky from time to time, as if expecting rain. The man in the beret interrupted me once, shouting: "I don't want to risk it! I'm leaving - you do what you want!" - after which he turned and ran downhill. But the other two remained and heard me out to the end, while I kept trying to guess my fate from their faces, without seeing anything good for myself. And then a saving thought came into my head, and forgetting everything I had just said, I burst out: "Keep in mind, gentlemen, that I am Mr. Charon's father-in-law."

"Who's Mr. Charon?" asked the insurgent with glasses.

"The chief editor of the newspaper in this area."

"So what?" asked the insurgent with glasses, and the officer kept surveying the sky.

I really got scared: they obviously didn't know Charon. But anyway I said, "My son-in-law took his gun and left home on the very first day."

"Is that so?" said the insurgent with glasses. "That's to his credit."

"That's a load of bull," said the officer. "What's going on in the city? Where are the troops?"

"I don't know," I said. "Everything's quiet with us in the city."

"Is there free access to the city?" asked the officer.

"I believe there is," I said and considered it my duty to add: "But you may be stopped by the men of the city's Voluntary Anti-Martian Patrol."

"What?" said the officer, and for the first time something like surprise registered on his hardened face. He even stopped looking at the sky and looked at me. "What patrol?"

"The Anti-Martian," I said. "Commanded by Noncommissioned Officer Polyphemus. Perhaps you know him? He's an invalid."

'The devil knows what to make of it," said the officer. "Can you lead us into the city?"

My heart sank. "Certainly," I said, "but my automobile ..."

"Yes," said the officer. "What's wrong with it?"

I plucked up courage and lied: "It seems the motor froze."

The officer whistled and without another word turned and disappeared in the wheat. The insurgent with glasses continued to eye me closely and then suddenly asked, "Do you have any grandchildren?"

"Yes!" I lied in complete desperation. "Two! One's still at the breast...."

He nodded sympathetically. "That's terrible," he said. "That torments me most of all. They know nothing, and now they will never know anything. ..."

I didn't understand a word he was saying, and I didn't want to understand, I only prayed that he would soon leave and not do anything to me. For some reason I suddenly imagined that this quiet fellow with glasses was the most terrible of the lot. For several seconds he awaited my answer, and then tossed his machine gun over his shoulder and said, "I advise you to get the hell out of here. Goodbye."

I didn't even wait for him to go in the wheat. I turned and walked as fast as I could down the hill toward town. As if some storm carried me on its wings. I wasn't aware of my legs, I didn't notice my short-windedness, I seemed to hear some mechanical rumbling and buzzing behind my back, but I didn't even turn around and simply tried to run. But I hadn't gotten very far when a small truck full of farmers turned out toward me from the crossroad. I was nearly unconscious, but found the strength to stand across their way. I waved my arms and shouted: "Stop! Not that way! Partisans ahead!"

The truck stopped and I was surrounded by rough simple people, for some reason armed with rifles. They grabbed me by the chest, shook me and cursed me with filthy language; I understood nothing, I was horrified and only after a while figured out that they had taken me for an accomplice of the partisans. My legs gave way under me, but here the driver got out of the cabin, and luckily he turned out to be a former student of mine.

"Hey, what are you guys doing!,, he yelled, grabbing their upraised threatening hands. 'That's Mr. Apollo, the town teacher! I know him."

Not immediately, but eventually they all calmed down, and I told them what I had seen.

"Aha," said the driver. "We knew it. Now we'll catch them. Let's go, you guys."

I wanted to continue on my way to the city, but he convinced me that it would be safer to stay with them, and he would fix my car in good time, after they had caught the bandits. They sat me in the cabin, and the truck rolled to the scene of the tragedy. There was the top of the rise, there was my automobile, but the road ahead was completely empty. There were no bodies, no fragments, only burned spots on the asphalt and a little dent in the place where the explosion had occurred.

"Pretty obvious," said the driver, stopping the truck. "They've already cleaned up. There they go flying ..."

Everyone started yelling and pointing at the horizon in the direction of Marathon, but no matter how I stared into the untroubled sky with my one good eye, I couldn't see anything.

Then the farmers, with an alacrity demonstrating a certain amount of training, without any unnecessary fuss or argumentation, split up into two groups of ten men each. These groups spread out into two chains and began the comb through the wheat - one to the right and one to the left.

"They have machine guns," I warned them, "grenades too, it seems."

"We are well aware of that," I was answered, and after a while shouts announced that the search party had hit on a trail.

Meanwhile the driver was fixing my car, while I, sitting in the back seat, let myself fall into a blessed half-sleep, having finally managed to calm my nerves. The driver not only got rid of the problem (it turned out to be an air lock in the fuel line) but also cleaned up the front seat, the splattered steering wheel and dashboard. Tears of gratitude burst from my eyes, I shook his hand and paid him as much as I could. He was satisfied. This simple, good man (I can't recall his name) turned out to be quite talkative, unlike most farmers, who are also simple and good, but stern and tight-lipped. He explained what had been going on.

It turned out that the insurgents, whom the peasant folk simply call bandits, had shown up in the area the very day after the arrival of the Martians. At first they were friendly toward the farmers, and it was learned that most of them were residents of Marathon, people well educated as a rule and harmless at first glance, if you don't count the military men. Their intentions remained moot to the farmers. In the beginning they encouraged the villagers to rise up against the new regime, but their reasons for the necessity of this were vague - they all kept repeating that it meant the ruination of culture, degeneration and other bookish things of little interest to the man in the village. Nevertheless, the farmers fed them and gave them shelter, because the situation was still unclear and no one knew as yet what to expect from the new regime. When it came out that nothing bad and only good was to be seen from the new powers, when the powers bought up the crop (not only the standing crop, but also the shoots) at a good price, when they made a generous advance on the new blue wheat, when money seemed to pour from heaven for the previously useless stomach juice and when, on the other hand, it was learned that the bandits were laying ambushes for the representatives of the administration as they were transporting money to the village, when a deputy from Marathon let them know that this outrage must be brought to a swift end for the good of everyone, then the farmers' attitude toward the insurgents changed completely.

Several times we interrupted our conversation and listened. Occasional shots could be heard from the fields, and every time we nodded at each other and winked with satisfaction. By now I had completely recovered and sat down at the wheel with the intention of turning around and driving home. (I had no thought, of course, of continuing my trip to Marathon. God be with him, that Alcimus, if this is what happens on the road.) At this moment, the search party returned to the highway. At first four farmers dragged two unmoving bodies to the truck. One of the dead men I recognized - it was the man in the beret whom the officer had called an engineer. The other, a young man, was unknown to me. With some relief I saw that fortunately he was not dead, but only seriously wounded. Then the rest of the search party returned in a mass, talking merrily to one another. They led forward a prisoner with tied hands whom I also recognized, although he was now without glasses. It was a complete rout, not one of the farmers had suffered. I felt a great moral satisfaction seeing how these simple people, still apparently fired up by the battle, nevertheless showed unquestionable spiritual nobility by addressing the defeated enemy in almost chivalrous terms. They bandaged the wounded man and laid him fairly gently in the back of the truck. And although they didn't untie the prisoner's hands, they gave him something to drink and stuck a cigarette in his mouth.

"Well, they've done a good job," said my friend the driver. "Now it'll be a bit quieter around here."

I considered it my duty to inform him that there were at least five insurgents.

"No matter," he answered. "That means two got away. They won't get far. Either in our district or the next, it's the same thing. They'll get kilt or caught."

"And what are you going to do with these three?" I asked.

"Drive 'em away. About forty kilometers from here there's a Martian post. They take all kinds there: dead or alive, however you bring 'em."

I thanked him and again shook his hand, and he headed for his truck, saying to the others, "What d'ya say, let's get a move-on."

And here they led the prisoner past me: he stopped for a moment and peered at my face with his myopic eyes. Perhaps it only seemed that way to me. Now I hope that it only seemed that way to me. Because in his eyes there was something that made my heart sink. Miserable world! No, I'm not justifying that man. He's a radical, he's a partisan, he has committed murder and should be punished, but still I'm not blind. I saw clearly that this was a noble man. Not a black-shirt, not a goon, but a man with convictions. However, I hope now that I made a mistake. All my life I have suffered because I think too well of people.

The truck rolled away in one direction, I in the other, and an hour later I was already home, completely bushed, aggravated and sick. I will note, by the way, that Mr. Nicostratus was sitting in the living room and Artemis was treating him to tea. But I was in no mood for them. Hermione started to fuss over me, turned back the bedspread, put an ice pack over my heart, and soon I fell asleep, and when I woke up during the night I knew that my eczema was getting worse again. It was a horrible, tormenting night.

Temperature: +17° C, cloud cover: 10, pouring rain.

Yes, they are rebels, people who destroy the peace and quiet. Yet I can't help but feel sorry for them, soaked to the bone, dirty, chased like wild beasts. And in the name of what? What is this - anarchism? A protest against injustice? What injustice? I simply don't understand them. Strange, now I remember that during the search there were no bursts of machine-gun fire nor grenade explosions. They must have run out of ammunition.

June 11 (midnight)

Hermione wanted me to spend today in bed, but I didn't obey her, and rightly so. By midday I felt quite well, and right after lunch I decided to go to town. Man is weak. I won't conceal the fact that I couldn't wait to tell the boys about the terrible and tragic events I had had the misfortune to witness yesterday. True, by lunchtime these events appeared to me in more a romantic light than a tragic one. My story had a huge success at The Five Spot, questions were hurled at me, and my petty vanity was fully satisfied. It was amusing to look at Polyphemus. (He, by the way, is the only member of the Anti-Martian Patrol to still drag a shotgun around with him.) When I reported my conversation with the officer-rebel to the boys, Polyphemus began to act important, assuming himself to be a part of the desperate and dangerous activity of the insurgents. He even went so far as to call the insurgents brave lads, even though they were acting outside of the law. What he meant by this, I don't know - in fact, no one knew. He also declared that in the insurgents' shoes he would have shown "that peasant rabble" what a pound of smoke was worth, and then a fight almost broke out, because Myrtilus's brother is a farmer and Myrtilus himself comes from peasant stock. I don't like arguments, can't stand them, so while the disputants were wrangling I went off to the mayor's office.

Mr. Nicostratus was a model of politeness with me. He inquired considerately about my health and listened to my tale of yesterday's adventure with great sympathy. And he wasn't the only one - all the other employees left their current business and gathered around me, so I enjoyed a complete success here as well. Everyone agreed that I had acted courageously and that my behavior spoke to my credit. I had to shake a lot of hands, and pretty Thyone even asked my permission to kiss me, which permission I granted, of course, with pleasure. (Blast it, I haven't been kissed by young girls for such a long time! I must admit I'd even forgotten how delightful it is.) Regarding my pension, Mr. Nicostratus assured me that everything would probably be all right, and he informed me in the greatest confidence that the matter of taxes had now definitely been decided: beginning in July taxes would be collected in stomach juice.

This engaging conversation was unfortunately interrupted by an outright scandal. The door of the mayor's office suddenly burst open and Mr. Corybantus appeared on the threshold with his back to us, shouting at Mr. Mayor that he would not let this pass, this was a violation of the freedom of speech, this was corruption, Mr. Mayor should remember the lamentable fate of Mr. Laomedon, and so on. Mr. Mayor also talked in a raised voice, but his timbre was a bit softer than Mr. Corybantus's, and I couldn't understand what he was saying. Mr. Corybantus at long last went away, slamming the door forcefully, and then Mr. Nicostratus explained to me what it was all about.

It happens that Mr. Mayor fined our newspaper and closed it for a week because the issue the day before yesterday had published some verses sent in by a certain XYZ, which contained these lines:

And where the sky meets with the Earth, The planet Mars burns bright and fierce.

Mr. Corybantus refused to submit to Mr. Mayor's decision, and for the second day now he has been cursing him over the telephone and in person. Discussing the affair, Mr. Nicostratus and I came to the same conclusion, namely that both sides in this dispute are right in their own way and wrong in their own way. On the one hand, the penalty Mr. Mayor leveled at the newspaper is excessively severe, especially since the poem in its entirety is absolutely harmless, as it speaks only of the author's unrequited love for the night fairy. But on the other hand, the situation is such that you shouldn't tease the geese: Mr. Mayor has enough troubles without this, if only the same old Minotaur, who got plastered again the day before yesterday and ran his stinking cistern into a Martian car.

Returning to The Five Spot, I joined the boys again. The argument between Polyphemus and Myrtilus had already been cleared up, and conversation was proceeding in the usual friendly atmosphere. Not without satisfaction, I noticed that my story had apparently led the collected minds down the same path. They were talking about insurgents, the military methods at the Martians' disposal and similar topics.

Morpheus related that not far from Miletus a Martian flying machine had made a forced landing because the pilot was not accustomed to the increased force of gravity; it was then attacked by a group of malefactors, but it shot down every last one of them with a special electric gun, after which it blew up, leaving a huge hole with glass sides. All of Miletus was supposedly taking trips to look at the hole.

Myrtilus, repeating what his farmer brother had told him, said that there was a ferocious band of Amazons attacking the Martians and abducting them for the purpose of procreation. One-legged Polyphemus, for his part, said the following. Last night, as he was patrolling Park Street, four Martian cars slipped noiselessly up on him. An unfamiliar voice, in broken speech and with an unpleasant lisp, asked him how to get to the tavern, and although the tavern does not represent any governmental significance, Polyphemus refused to answer out of pride and contempt for the conquerors, so the Martians had to move on with long faces. Polyphemus assured us that his life had been hanging by a thread all the while, he had even supposedly spied long black barrels aimed right at him, but he had never flinched and never budged.

"What's wrong with you, would it put you out to tell them?,, asked Myrtilus, who hadn't forgotten the insult to his family. "I know bastards like that. You drive into an unfamiliar place, you feel like having a drink, and for no reason at all they won't tell you where the tavern is."

It almost came to a fight again, but here Pandareus came up and, smiling joyfully, reported that finally Minotaur had been deported from our city. The Martians had deported him. They suspected him of connections of terrorists and of sabotage. We all objected: to leave the city without a honey-dipper in the hottest time of the year - why, it's a crime!

"Enough!" roared one-legged Polyphemus. "We've suffered this damned yoke long enough! Patriots, follow my command! Fa-a-all in!"

We had already begun to form lines when Pandareus calmed everyone by saying that the Martians intended to begin work next week laying in a sewer system, and meanwhile a young policeman would be put in place of Minotaur. Everyone said that his was another matter, and again they turned to conversation about the terrorists. And about how dirty it was to lay ambushes.

Dymus, rolling his eyes, told us a frightening story. For three days now some kind of people have been roaming the town and treating everyone they meet with candy. "You eat a piece of that candy - and boink! - you've had it." They hope to poison all the Martians this way. We, of course, didn't believe his story, but it was scary anyway.

Here Calais, who had been twitching and sputtering for some time, suddenly babbled: "B-b-but Apollo here has a son-in-law who's a terrorist."

Everyone sort of moved away from me, and Pandareus, thrusting out his lower jaw, announced weightily: 'That's right. We have information to that effect."

I became highly indignant and told them all that, first, a father-in-law is not responsible for his son-in-law; second, Pandareus himself has a nephew who spent five years inside for licentious behavior; third, I have always been at loggerheads with Charon, as anyone could confirm; and fourth, I know nothing of the sort about Charon - the man left on assignment and neither hide nor hair of him has been seen since. These were unpleasant moments, but the flimsiness of the accusation was so obvious that everything ended happily and the conversation turned to stomach juice.

It turns out that the boys have been giving stomach juice for two days already and receiving cash for it on the spot. Only I am left out. In some incomprehensible way I am always left out of something profitable to me. There are such hapless people in the world: in the barracks they are always cleaning the urinals, at the front they fall into the "buckets," they are the first to get the worst, the last to get the best. That's the sort of man I am. Well, so be it. All the boys were boasting about how pleased they were now. How could they not be!

Here a Martian car drove across the square, and one-legged Polyphemus pronounced thoughtfully: "What do you think, old buddies, if we let her have it with the shotgun, would it go through or not?"

"Well, if it's a bullet," said Silenus, "then it ought to go through."

"That depends on where you hit it," objected Myrtilus. "If it's fore or aft, then no way will it go through."

"And if it's broadside?" asked Polyphemus.

"Broadside it'll probably go through," answered Myrtilus.

I was about to say that a grenade wouldn't even go through it, but Pandareus beat me to the punch by saying profoundly, "No, old boys, you're arguing over nothing. They're invulnerable."

"Broadside they're invulnerable?" asked Myrtilus venomously.

"All over," said Pandareus.

"What, even by a bullet?" asked Myrtilus.

"Even to cannonfire," said Pandareus with great gravity.

Here everyone began to shake his head and slap Pandareus on the back. "Yeah, Pan," they said. "You're the one. You slipped up that time, Pander, old fellow. You didn't think, old-timer, you just babbled." And grouchy Paralus rubbed it in right away, saying that if you fired a cannon at Pandareus broadside, you might make a dent, but if you hit him aft, in the head, it would just bounce off.

Well, Pandareus puffed up, buttoned his jacket all the way up to the top button, rolled his crayfish eyes and bawled: "You've had your say - that's it! Dis-s-perse! In the name of the law."

Losing no time, I headed for the donor station. Of course, failure awaited me once again. They didn't take any juice from me, so I didn't get any money. It turns out they have a rule that they must draw off the juice on an empty stomach, and I had had lunch only two hours before. They gave me a donor card and invited me to come tomorrow morning. By the way, I ought to say that the donor station produced a most favorable impression on me. The most recent equipment. The probe is smeared with the very best brands of Vaseline. The stomach juice is obtained automatically, but under the supervision of an experienced physician, not some kind of ruffian. The personnel are without exception polite and well mannered; it's immediately apparent that they are well paid. Everything is spanking clean, the furniture is new. While waiting your turn in line you can watch television or read fresh newspapers. And what kind of line is there? Far shorter than in the tavern. And the money is paid out immediately, straight from the machine. Yes, a high level of culture, humaneness and concern for the donor are felt throughout. And to think that only three days ago this house was the den of such a man as Mr. Laomedon!

However, thoughts of my son-in-law did not leave me, and I felt it necessary to discuss this vexing new problem with Achilles. I found him, as always, behind the cash register looking through his issue of Cosmos. The tale of my adventures made a big impression on him, and I felt that he was looking at me now with completely different eyes. But when we came to Charon, he simply shrugged his shoulders and said that my course of action and the dangers I had faced would not only fully rehabilitate me, but possibly Charon as well. Besides, he pretty much doubted that Charon was capable of becoming involved in anything illicit. Charon, he claimed, was most likely in Marathon helping to re-establish order, thereby trying to do something useful for his hometown, as behooves every cultured citizen, and all those envious townsmen, those Pandareuses and Calaises, who can only spout irresponsible gibberish, were simply slandering him.

I had my doubts on that score, but naturally I kept silent and simply marveled that we, the residents of really only a small town, knew each other so poorly. I realized it had been pointless to talk about this matter with Achilles, and so, pretending that his considerations had calmed me, I turned the conversation to stamps. But here is where the surprising event occurred.

I recall that at first I was speaking with some constraint, because my main purpose was somehow to distract Achilles from our conversation about Charon. But it happened that we began to talk about that blessed inverted lithographic overprint. Some time ago I had expounded completely irrefutable proof to Achilles that this was a forgery, and it seemed the question had been settled. However, the day before, Achilles had read some miserable pamphlet and deemed himself qualified to put forward his own considerations. This was something unprecedented in our relationship. Naturally, I lost my temper, flew into a rage and said straight out that Achilles didn't know anything about philately, a mere year ago he didn't know the difference between a Klemmtasche and a Klassier and it was no wonder that his collection was chock full of defective specimens. Achilles also flared up, and we began a real knock-down drag-out fight, of which I am capable only with Achilles and only over stamps.

I seemed to become vaguely aware, while we were arguing, that someone had come into the drugstore and extended a paper to Achilles over my shoulder, and Achilles had fallen silent for a moment, which silence I immediately used to drive a wedge into his incompetent observations. After that I recall an irritating difficulty, something extraneous persistently pressing into my consciousness, preventing me from thinking systematically and logically. However, this eventually passed, and the next stage of this occurrence, which is most interesting from the psychological point of view, was the moment when our argument ended and we fell silent, tired and somewhat offended at each other.

I recall that at that precise moment I suddenly felt an overwhelming need to look over the premises, and I experienced a dull surprise when I discovered no particular change. At the same time I distinctly knew that some kind of change should have occurred during our argument. Here I noticed that Achilles was also experiencing some emotional discomfort. He also looked around and then walked along the counter, glancing under it. Finally he said, "Tell me, would you, Phoebus - didn't someone come in here?" He was disturbed by exactly the same thing as I. His question dotted all the i's, and I understood what all my confusion was about.

"A blue hand!" I exclaimed, enlightened by a suddenly bright recollection. As if before my very eyes, I could see blue fingers holding the piece of paper.

"No, not a hand!" said Achilles excitedly. "A tentacle! Like an octopus!"

"But I distinctly remember fingers...."

"A tentacle, like a polyp!" Achilles repeated, looking around feverishly. Then he grabbed the book of prescriptions from the counter and hurriedly flipped the pages. I went numb all over from a dark foreboding. Holding the piece of paper in his hand, he slowly raised his wide-open eyes to me, and I knew what he would now say.

"Phoebus," he uttered in a hushed voice. "It was a Martian."

We were both shaken, and Achilles, as a man close to medicine, considered it necessary to fortify me and himself with cognac, a bottle of which he took from a big cardboard box labeled "Norsulphazolum." Yes, while we were arguing over that inauspicious overprint, a Martian had stopped in the drugstore, handed Achilles a written order to turn over to the bearer all medicinal compounds containing narcotics, and Achilles, without understanding or remembering anything, had handed him a package of such medicines prepared in advance, after which the Martian had gone away without leaving anything in our memory besides snatches of recollections and a dim image caught out of the corner of the eye.

I distinctly recalled a blue hand with short sparse hairs and meaty fingers without nails, and I was amazed that a sight like that did not instantly knock out of my head any ability to carry on an abstract argument.

Achilles did not recall any hand, but he did remember a long tentacle, incessantly pulsating, extended toward him as if out of nowhere. Besides this, he recalled that the sight of this tentacle had caused him extreme irritation, for he considered it a joke that was quite out-of-place. He recalled also how he had angrily tossed the package of medicines on the counter without looking, but on the other hand he absolutely did not recall whether he had read the prescription and entered it in the book, although it was obvious that he had read it (since he had released the medicines) and had entered it (since it was there).

We drank another glass of cognac, and Achilles called to mind that the Martian had stood to the left of me and had worn a fashionable sweater with a V neck, and I recalled that on one of the blue fingers there had been a sparkling ring of white metal with a precious stone. Besides this, I recalled the sound of an automobile. Achilles wiped his brow and announced that the sight of the prescription reminded him of the sensation of dissatisfaction at someone's attempts, insistent to the point of impoliteness, to break into our argument with some completely ridiculous point of view about philately in general and inverted overprints in particular.

Then I remembered that, yes, the Martian had actually spoken and his voice had been piercing and unpleasant.

"Rather, it was low and condescending," objected Achilles.

However, I held my own view, and Achilles, getting hot again, called his assistant out of the laboratory and asked him what sounds he had heard during the last hour. The assistant, an uncommonly dim-witted young man, blinked his stupid eyes and mumbled that all the time he heard only our voices, but once it seemed that someone had turned on the radio, but he hadn't paid any special attention to it. We sent the young pharmacist away and downed another drop of cognac. Our memories cleared up completely, and although we differed in our opinion of the Martian's appearance as before, we fully agreed on the sequence of events. The Martian, without a doubt, had come to the drugstore in a car; he did not turn off the motor, he entered the premises, he stopped to the left of me, almost beside me, and he stood for a while without moving, examining us and listening to our conversation. (My flesh crawled when I realized my complete helplessness at that terrible moment.) Then he made several remarks to us, apparently concerning philately and apparently completely incompetent, then he extended the instructions to Achilles. Achilles took it, looked at it hastily and stuck it in the book. Further, Achilles, put out by this intrusion, handed over the package of medicines, and the Martian left, having understood that we did not wish to admit him into the conversation. Thus, leaving aside the details, there arose the image of this creature who, although poorly versed in matters of philately, was by no means devoid of a proper education and a certain humanity, if you take into consideration that he could have done with us whatever he'd wanted. We drank another glass of cognac and felt that we could no longer remain here and keep the boys in ignorance of this occurrence. Achilles hid the bottle, left the assistant pharmacist in charge and we beat it to the tavern on the double.

The boys reacted to our story about the Martian's visit in various ways. One-legged Polyphemus openly called it a lie. "Just take a sniff, they're reeking of it. They've guzzled so much, they're seeing blue devils."

Rational Silenus proposed that it had not actually been a Martian, but some kind of Negro - sometimes Negroes have a bluish tint to their skin.

Paralus - well, he was the same old Paralus. "A good druggist we've got," he said grouchily. "Someone unknown comes from somewhere unknown, slips him some unknown piece of paper, and he gives it to him without a peep. No, we won't build a reasonable society with druggists like that. What kind of druggist is it who doesn't know what's going on because of his lousy stamps?"

But all the others were on our side, the whole tavern gathered around us. Even the golden youth with Mr. Nicostratus in the lead poured over from the bar to listen. They made us repeat again and again where I had stood and where the Martian had stood when he'd extended his extremity, and so on. Very soon I noticed that Achilles was beginning to embellish the story with new details, shocking for the most part. (Such as that the Martian blinked only two eyes like us when he was silent, but when he opened his mouth some additional eyes opened, one red, the other white.) I commented on this, but he objected that cognac and brandy had a remarkable effect on human memory, this was, so to say, a medical fact. I decided not to argue with him, asked lapetus to serve me supper and, laughing to myself, began to observe how Achilles was surely becoming his own worst enemy. In ten minutes or so they all knew he was talking through his hat, and they stopped paying any attention to him. The golden youth returned to the bar, and soon the same old complaint was heard from there: "I'm tired of it…. It's so dull around here. Martians? Bull, senility.... What should we knock off tonight, sports?"

At our table the old argument about stomach juice was renewed. What in the world is it, what good is it, what do the Martians need it for, and what do we ourselves need it for? Achilles explained that man needs stomach juice for the digestion of food, it would be impossible to digest food without it. But his authority had already been undermined, and no one believed him.

"You ought to shut your trap, you old enema bag," Polyphemus told him. "What do you mean, impossible. This is the third day I've given the juice, and nothing's wrong, Fm digesting. You should digest so good.. .."

In despair they turned to Calais for consultation, but this naturally led to nothing. After prolonged spasms, which kept the entire tavern on tenterhooks, he only burst out: "A g-g-gendarme's already an old man at thirty, if you really want to know." These words referred to some half-forgotten conversation which had taken place at The Five Spot sometime before lunch, and in fact was meant not for us, but for Pandareus, who had gone to work a long time before. We left Calais to work up an answer to our question, while we fell to speculation.

Silenus proposed that the civilization of Mars had come to a physiological dead end; they no longer could produce their own juice, and so they had to locate other sources.

Iapetus put in his two bits from behind the bar, stating that the Martians use the stomach juice as a ferment for the production of a special kind of energy. "Like atomic energy," he added as an afterthought.

But that fool Dymus, who had never distinguished himself for bold flights of fancy, stated that human stomach juice for a Martian was the same as cognac or beer for us, or say, juniper vodka, and with this statement spoiled the appetite of everyone who was just beginning to eat.

Someone proposed that the Martians obtained gold or rare metals from stomach juice, and this obviously illiterate proposal prompted Morpheus to a very true thought. "However you look at it, old buddies," he said, "whether they get gold or energy out of it, you must realize that our stomach juice is a very important thing for the Martians. Have they pulled a fast one on us, huh?"

At first no one understood, but finally we caught on that no one really knew the true price of stomach juice or what kind of price the Martians had set. It was quite possible that the Martians, being practical people, as we must suppose, were making a disproportionately large profit out of this enterprise, taking advantage of our ignorance.

"They're cutting us down to dirt cheap," one-legged Polyphemus flared up in a white heat, "and then those rotten bastards will drive it up to the true price on some comet!"

I ventured to correct him, that it's not on any comet, but on a planet, to which he responded with his usual vulgarity that I should have my eye treated and then get into arguments. But that's not the point.

Morpheus's idea got us all excited, and a very pithy and valuable discussion might have developed, but at this point Myrtilus barged into the tavern with his farmer brother, both stewed to the gills. It turned out that Myrtilus's brother had been experimenting with the distillation of malt from the blue wheat and today, at long last, his experiments had been crowned with success. Two hefty jugs of the first lot of blue brew were set up on the table. Everyone took an immediate interest and began to sample it, and I must say that ''blue-beer" made a big impression on us. As luck would have it, Myrtilus invited Iapetus to the table to give it a try. Iapetus drank two short glasses, stood a moment screwing up his left eye, as if cogitating, and then suddenly said, "Pack off, I never want to see you here again." This was said in such a tone of voice that Myrtilus, without saying a word, grabbed the empty jugs and his groggy brother and cleared out. Iapetus surveyed us with a heavy eye and with the words, 'That's a new one - coming into my establishment with their own swill," he returned to the bar. To smooth things over, we all ordered a round, but the previous free and easy atmosphere had vanished. After sitting for another half hour, I headed home.

In the living room Mr. Nicostratus, occupying Charon's armchair, was sitting across from Artemis and drinking tea with preserves. I didn't interfere in their affair. First of all, Charon, it seems, has been cut off entirely, and no one can say if he will ever return at all. Second, Hermione was somewhere in the immediate vicinity, and I stank so much of alcohol that I could smell it myself. Therefore I preferred to slip quietly to my room, without attracting anyone's attention. I changed clothes and looked at the paper. It's simply amazing! Sixteen pages of type, and nothing of substance. Like chewing a wad of cotton. The press conference of the president was published. I read it twice and didn't understand anything - nothing but stomach juice.

I'm going to go see how Hermione feels.

June 12

Temperature: +12°C, cloud cover: 0, no wind. Terrible belching from that bluebeer. My migraine has flared up. Sat home all day. A new gastronomical novelty has appeared: blue bread. Hermione praised it, Artemis liked it too, but I just ate it without any appetite. It's bread like any other bread, only blue.

June 13

Finally, it seems, summer weather has arrived. Temperature: +22° C, cloudy ...

What things are going on! I don't even know how to begin. In regard to my pension nothing is known, but in the final analysis it's not a matter of my pension anymore. Just now, when I began today's entry, I suddenly heard a car approaching. I thought it was only Myrtilus bringing the quart of bluebeer he promised from the farm, and I looked out to see. As it happened, I looked out at just the right time. At first I saw an unfamiliar car under the streetlight, very deluxe, and then I noticed that coming across the garden with a decisive step, straight toward the bench where Artemis and Mr. Nicostratus had settled down since evening, was Charon. Before I could blink my eye, Mr. Nicostratus had flown higgledy-piggledy over the fence. With superhuman strength Charon hurled his walking stick and hat after him, but Mr. Nicostratus did not stop to pick them up and only ran faster. Then Charon turned to Artemis. It was hard for me to see what happened between them, but I have the impression that at first Artemis tried to fall in a faint; however, when Charon pasted her one up against the side of the head, she changed her mind and decided instead to show her celebrated temperament. She let out a long, ear-splitting scream and slashed at Charon's physiognomy with her fingernails. I repeat, I did not see all of this. But when I looked into the living room a few minutes later, Charon was pacing from corner to corner like a caged tiger, holding his hands behind his back, and a fresh scratch was turning crimson on his nose. Artemis was setting the table matter-of-factly, but I noticed that her face looked a little bit asymmetrical. I can't stand family scenes, I get all weak inside and feel like going away somewhere where I will see and hear nothing. However, Charon noticed me before I could slip out and contrary to all expectations greeted me so cordially and warmly that I considered it impossible to go into the living room and strike up a conversation with him.

Above all, I was pleasantly surprised by the fact that Charon looked quite unlike what I had expected. This was no longer that shaggy and raggedy bum who had clanked his gun around and railed at me a week ago. In fact, I had expected him to be even more ragged and dirty. But before me sat the previous Charon of peaceful times, smoothly shaven, neatly combed, elegantly and tastefully dressed. Only the crimson scratch on his nose somewhat spoiled the overall impression, and also his complexion, which was unusually swarthy, testified to the fact that in recent days this office worker had spent a lot of time under the open sky.

Hermione came in wearing hairpins, excused herself for her appearance and also sat down at the table. And there we sat, the four of us, just as in the old days, one peaceful family. Until the women cleared the table and left, the conversation revolved around general subjects: the weather, health, how Charon looked. But once we were left alone, Charon lit up a cigar and said, looking at me strangely, "Well, what do you think, father, is our cause lost?"

In answer I simply shrugged my shoulders, although I very much felt like saying that if anyone's cause was lost, it certainly wasn't ours. But then, in my view, Charon didn't expect an answer. Around the women he had kept calm, and only now did I notice that he was in a state of extreme agitation, almost to the point of sickness, that state in which a man is able to switch abruptly from nervous laughter to nervous weeping, when everything is bubbling inside him and he feels an overwhelming need to release this bubbling in words and therefore talks, talks, talks. And Charon talked.

There is no more future for people, he said. Man has ceased to be the pinnacle of nature. For now and evermore and throughout all eternity man would be an ordinary phenomenon of nature like a tree or horse, nothing more. Culture and progress together had lost all meaning. Mankind no longer required self-development, it would be developed from outside, and so schools would no longer be needed, institutes and laboratories would no longer be needed, social thought would no longer be needed - in a word, everything that distinguished man from beast and was called civilization would no longer be needed. As a factory of stomach juice, Albert Einstein was no better than Pandareus, most likely worse, since Pandareus was marked by rare gluttony. Not in the boom of a cosmic catastrophe, not in the flames of nuclear war and not even in the clutches of overpopulation would the history of mankind come to an end, but, don't you see, in calm, sated tranquility.

"Just think," he said with his voice breaking, holding his head in his hands, "civilization wasn't destroyed by ballistic missiles, but by nothing more than a handful of coppers for a glass of stomach juice.. .."

He spoke, of course, much longer and much more effectively, but I understand abstract reasoning poorly and remembered only what I remembered. To be frank, he succeeded in depressing me. However, I rather quickly understood that all this was simply the hysterical verborrhea of a cultured man who had experienced the collapse of his personal ideals. And so I felt it necessary to raise an objection. Not, of course, because I hoped to convince him of the opposite, but because his judgments deeply wounded me, they struck me as grandiose and immodest, and besides I wanted to get away from that oppressive feeling produced by his lamentations.

"You've had too easy a life, my son," I said pointedly. "You're getting picky. You don't know anything about life. Right away one can see that you've never been bashed in the teeth, youVe never frozen in the trenches and you've never hauled logs in prison. YouVe always had enough to eat and money to pay for it. YouVe gotten used to looking at the world through the eyes of a god in heaven, that superman of yours. What a pity - civilization has been sold for a handful of coppers! Just say thanks that you're given these coppers for it! For you, of course, they're not worth much. But for a widow who has to bring up three children, to feed them, educate them, raise them? And for Polyphemus, a cripple who receives a meager pension? And a farmer? What would you offer a farmer? Some dubious little social ideas? Booklets, brochures? Your esthetic philosophy? Well, a farmer would spit on the whole deal! He needs clothes, machines, he needs the certainty of tomorrow! He needs the constant possibility of raising a crop and receiving a good price for it! Could you give him that? You and your civilization! No one has been able to give him that for ten thousand years, but the Martians did it! Where's the wonder that the farmers now hound you like wild beasts? No one needs you and your discussions, your snobbery, your abstract prophecies which so easily change into machine-gun fire. The farmer doesn't need you, the city dweller doesn't need you, the Martians don't need you. I am even certain that most reasonable educated people don't need you. You imagine yourself the flower of civilization, but in fact you are the mold growing over its juices. You've elevated yourself in your own mind and now you imagine that your downfall is the downfall of all civilization."

It seemed to me that I had literally slain him with my speech. He sat with his face in his hands, shaking all over. It was so pitiful that my heart flooded with blood.

"Charon," I said as gently as possible, "my child! Try for a moment to descend from the cloudy spheres to the sinful earth. Try to understand that what man needs most in the world is tranquility and the certainty of tomorrow. After all, nothing so terrible has happened. Here you say that man has been converted into a stomach-juice factory. Those are ringing words, Charon, but in fact the reverse has occurred. Man, coming upon new conditions of existence, has found an excellent way to utilize his physiological resources to simplify his position in the world. You call this slavery, but every reasonable man considers it an ordinary business deal which should be mutually profitable. What kind of slavery can it be if the reasonable man is already figuring out whether or not he is being cheated, and if he really is being cheated, I can assure you, he will have justice. You speak of the end of culture and civilization, but this is completely untrue! It's impossible even to say what you have in mind. The newspapers come out every day, new books are being published, new television shows are being created, industry is working. ... Charon! What more do you need! You've been left everything that you had: freedom of speech, self-determination, the constitution. Not only that, you've been protected from Mr. Laomedon! And, finally, you have been given a constant and reliable source of income, which doesn't depend on any competition."

I ended on this, because I discovered that Charon was by no means slain and was not sobbing, as it had seemed to me, but was giggling in the most indecent way. I considered myself highly offended, but here Charon said:

"Forgive me, for God's sake, I didn't want to offend you. I simply remembered an amusing story."

It happened that two days ago Charon and his group of five insurgents had seized a Martian car. How amazed they were when out of the car clambered a completely sober Minotaur with a portable device for sucking out stomach juice. "What d'ya say, fellows, feel like a drink?" he asked. "C'mon, I'll set you up right away. Who's first?" The insurgents were dumbfounded. When they recovered their senses, they half-heartedly slapped Minotaur around for being a traitor and then let him go with his car. They had thought of seizing the car to learn to drive it, and then to penetrate a Martian post with it and stage a battle there, but this episode had such an effect on them that they began to spit on everything. That very evening two of them went home, and the next day the rest of them were taken by the armers.

I didn't quite get the connection between this story and the topic of our conversation, but I was struck by the thought that Charon had consequently been held captive by the Marians.

"Yes," he answered by question, "that's why I was laughing. The Martians told me the same thing as you, point for point. True, a bit more coherently. And they especially emphasized that I was the elite of society, they felt deep respect for me and failed to understand why I and others like me were carrying out terroristic activities instead of forming a reasonable opposition. They proposed that we fight them by legal means, guaranteeing us complete freedom of the press and the right of assembly. Great fellows, the Martians - right?"

What could I answer him? Especially when it became clear that they had treated him most civilly, bathed him, clothed him, treated his wounds, given him an automobile confiscated from the owner of some opium den and let him go with their blessing.

'Words fail me," I said, throwing up my hands.

"Me too," replied Charon, darkening again. "Words still fail me too, but we must find them. We're worth a pittance if we don't find them."

After this he completely unexpectedly wished me a good night and went to his room, while I remained sitting there like a fool, seized by an unpleasant foreboding. Oh, we are going to have more trouble with Charon! Oh, we are for sure! And what a disgusting way to leave, without having finished the argument. It's already 1 a.m., and my eye is wide open.

Incidentally, today I gave stomach juice for the first time. No big deal, only it's unpleasant to swallow; but they say that soon you get used to it. If you give 200 grams every day, that makes 150 bills a month. Wow!

June 14

Temperature: +22° C, cloud cover: 0, no wind. The new stamps have finally come out. My God, how exquisite! I purchased the whole issue in quarter-sheet and then couldn't resist and bought the full sheets. Enough economizing. Now I can permit myself a few things. Went with Hermione to give stomach juice; from now on I'll go alone. There's a rumor that a notice arrived from the ministry of education confirming the previous status of pensions, however I failed to get any details. Mr. Nicostratus didn't come to work - he sent his younger brother to say he had caught the flu. People are saying, though, that he doesn't have the flu at all, but accidentally fell down somewhere and received internal injuries. Oh, you Charon! Artemis creeps as quiet as a mouse all through the house.

Yes, I completely forgot. I looked into the living room and saw Charon sitting there along with some pleasant gentleman with big glasses. I recognized him and literally turned to stone. It was the same insurgent whom the farmers had captured before my very eyes. He also recognized me and also turned to stone. We looked at each other for some time, then I recovered and bowed my way out. I don't know what he told Charon about me. But soon he left. I really mean it: this doesn't please me. If they plan to make a legal battle and organize all sorts of meetings, brochures and newspapers, as they were officially advised, then go right ahead. But if only once I see automatics and other such hardware in my home, then I beg your pardon, dear son-in-law. Here our paths must part. That's the most I can do.

To calm myself down, I just now re-read yesterday's entry of my conversation with Charon. In my opinion, my logic was flawless. He didn't even manage to make an objection. It's a shame, though, that I wrote it down more coherently and convincingly than I said it. I have absolutely no talent for speaking, that's my weak point.

The morning papers carried an interesting report on the general demobilization and demilitarization of the country. Thank God, they've finally thought of it! It must be that the Martians have taken the matter of defense entirely into their own hands, and now this defense won't cost us a penny, if you don't count stomach juice, of course. Nothing was said directly about this in the president's speech, but you could read it between the lines. The previous military expenditures, he said, will be used for raising the standard of living and developing shipbuilding. Certain difficulties now stand in the way of reducing the arms industry; however this will be a purely temporary phenomenon. And he also emphasized several times that no one will suffer from the reorganization. I take this to mean that the military industrialists and generals will get a lump sum. Rich people, these Martians! The demobilization has already begun. Paralus is spreading the rumor that the police will also be abolished. Pandareus wanted to haul him in, but we wouldn't let him. Rumors, of course, are only rumors, but if I were in Pandareus's shoes I would be more careful.

Actually, I don't feel like writing anything down today. I'm going to take the speech I made to Charon yesterday and make a clean copy. It's a good speech.

June 15

The morning has turned out exceptionally clear and pure. (Temperature: +21° C, cloud cover: 0, no wind.) How pleasant it is to get up early in the morning, when the sun has already dispersed the morning haze, but the air is still fresh and cool and preserves the nocturnal aromas. The minutest drops of dew tremble in myriad rainbows and flicker iridescently like precious stones on every blade of grass, every leaf, every web stretched at night by the industrious spider from his little home to the quivering twig. No, I don't do too well with artistic prose. On the one hand, everything seems to be in its proper place, it's beautiful, but all the same somehow... I don't know, something's not right. Well, so be it.

For the second day we are all enjoying an excellent appetite. They say it comes from the blue bread. Truly, it's a remarkable product. I never used to eat bread outside of sandwiches and generally ate little bread at all, but now I am literally stuffing myself with it. It melts in your mouth like a cookie, and it doesn't sit heavily on your stomach. Even Artemis, who always worried more about keeping her figure than keeping her family, can't control herself and eats like a young, healthy woman of her age should eat. Charon also eats it and praises it. In answer to my remarks, which are not entirely free of spite, he only answers, "One thing does not contradict the other, father. One thing does not contradict the other."

After breakfast I headed for the mayor's office and arrived just at the beginning of reception time. The boys had not yet come to The Five Spot. Mr. Nicostratus looked rather bad. With every movement he grimaced, grabbed his side and moaned quietly from time to time. He spoke in a pained whisper and paid no attention to his fingernails. During the course of our conversation he didn't once look at me, but he did speak politely, respectfully and without the slightest touch of his usual irony. A notice confirming the previous status of pension payments had indeed been received. My papers were probably at the minister's office. It seems likely that everything will turn out favorably and I will get the first category; however this will not prevent me from asking Mr. Mayor to send a special letter to the minister confirming my personal involvement in the armed struggle against the insurgents. This thought pleased me greatly, and Mr. Nicostratus and I agreed that I should compose a rough draft of such a communique, which he would edit and present to Mr. Mayor for consideration.

In the meantime the boys had gathered at The Five Spot. Morpheus was the last to arrive, and we fined him. Enough liberalism - we've neglected our club business in recent days. Everyone was terribly interested in one question: had the matter between Charon and Mr. Nicostratus been settled? They forced me to describe everything I had seen in great detail, and for a while one-legged Polyphemus argued with Silenus what part of Mr. Nicostratus exactly had been injured. As an experienced man and a noncommissioned officer, Polyphemus asserted that in such a scuffle Mr. Secretary's coccyx should have been injured, for only a well-placed kick with the point of the boot in the appropriate place could have caused Mr. Nicostratus to abandon the field of battle in the manner I had described. Silenus, as a man no less experienced and a former lawyer, objected that precisely the same effect was produced by a well-aimed blow to the body, and if you took into account the postures which Mr. Nicostratus now assumed, you had inevitably to conclude that a rib on his left side had been injured: either a crack, or perhaps a fracture. Both, however, agreed that the matter was far from settled and that Mr. Nicostratus, being young, hot-blooded and athletic, would not fail to meet Charon in some dark corner along with his buddies.

They also dunned me whether Artemis continued to be favorably inclined toward Mr. Nicostratus, and when I decisively refused to answer this tactless question, they concluded almost unanimously that yes, of course, she did.

"A woman is a woman," said grouchy Paralus. "One man is never enough for a woman, that's her biological nature."

I lost my temper and observed that when a woman is like that it lies more within the biological nature of certain men, such as Paralus, and everyone found my joke very witty, since they were fed up with Paralus and his grouchiness, and second, they recalled that in time past, before the war, his young wife had run off with a traveling salesman. A very propitious moment had arisen in which to put Paralus, with all his eternal quasi-philosophical sentiments, in his proper place.

Morpheus, who had already thought up a new wisecrack and was bursting with laughter in anticipation, grabbed everybody by the hands and shouted: "No, listen to what Fm going to say!" But here, as inopportunely as always, that old horse's ass Pandareus pushed his way in and without paying attention to the subject under discussion announced in his thunderous voice that a new fashion had come to us from abroad - two to four men living with one woman, just like cats. Well, what can you do! Just throw up your hands. Paralus immediately latched on to this pronouncement and at once changed the conversation to the subject of Pandareus.

"Yes, Pan," he said, "you're in good form today, old fellow. I haven't heard such things even from my younger son-in-law - the major."

Paralus's second son-in-law was known far beyond the city limits; it was impossible to restrain ourselves, and we all doubled over with laughter. But Paralus quickly topped that with a sorrowful look: "No, old boys, demilitarizing isn't enough. We ought to depolicetize or, if worse comes to worst, depandareusize."

Pandareus immediately puffed up like a blowfish, buttoned his jacket up to the top button and bawled: "You've had your say - that's all!..."

It was still too early to go to the donor station, so I headed for Achilles' place. I read him the fair copy of my speech to Charon. He listened to me with his mouth hanging open. It was a total success. Here are his precise words when I had finished reading: "That was written by a real orator, Phoebus! Where did you take it from?"

I posed a bit for better effect and then explained how it had come about. But he didn't believe me! He stated that a retired astronomy teacher simply wasn't capable of formulating the thoughts and aspirations of the simple people so accurately.

"Only great writers are capable of that," he said, "or great statesmen. But I see nothing of the sort in our country," he said, "neither great writers nor great statesmen.

"Phoebus, you stole it from the Martians," he said. "Admit it, you old duffer, I won't tell anybody."

I was nonplussed. His disbelief both flattered me and vexed me at the same time. And then he suddenly showed me a sealed envelope made of heavy black paper.

"What's that?" I asked with deliberate casualness, while my heart sensed disaster and sank with bad forebodings.

"Stamps," says the bold man. "Real ones. From there!"

I don't know how I managed to control myself. As if in a fog, I listened to his raptures, expressed with intentional sympathy. And he twirled the envelope under my nose and kept telling me what a rarity it was, how impossible it was to obtain them anywhere, what fabulous sums Chtonius had already offered him for them, and how adroitly he, Achilles, had acted by demanding stamps instead of money as compensation for the banned medicines. The sums which he casually named completely flabbergasted me. It turns out that the market price for Martian stamps is so high that no first-class pension and no stomach juice could ever alter my situation. But finally I recovered myself and had a brain wave. I asked Achilles to show me the stamps. And everything became clear. The Conner began to hedge: he lost his composure and babbled something about the stamps' being sensitive to light, like photograph paper, since they were from Mars. They could be examined only under a special light, and here, in the drugstore, there was no proper equipment. I took heart and asked him if I could drop by in the evening, before he went home. Utterly without life, he invited me, saying that, honestly, he didn't have the special equipment at home yet either, but he would try to think up something by tomorrow night. Now that I can believe. He will surely think up something. Most likely it will turn out that these stamps dissolve in the air or you can't look at them at all, but only feel them with your fingers.

In the heat of our discussion I suddenly heard someone's breathing by my left ear, and out of the corner of my eye I caught a movement beside me. I remembered at once the mysterious visitor and turned around sharply, but it was only Madam Persephone's maid, who had come to ask for something more reliable. Achilles went to the laboratory to search for a preparation which would satisfy Madam Persephone, and apparently he intended not to return until I had left. I left without concealing my irony.

At the donor station a pleasant surprise awaited me: the appropriate tests revealed that owing to my chronic internal irritations, my stomach juice must be put in the first category, so that for 100 grams of juice they are going to pay me 40 percent more than all the rest. Not only that, the medical attendant suggested that if I consume a moderate but sufficient quantity of bluebeer, I might get switched to the category of extra-fine and receive 70 to 80 percent more than 100 grams. I don't want to hex it, but finally it seems for the first time in my life I've lucked out a bit.

In the most sunny disposition I headed for the tavern and sat there till late at night. We had a great time. First, Iapetus is now doing a lively business in bluebeer, which the neighboring farmers supply him wholesale. Bluebeer makes you belch terribly, but it's cheap, goes down easy and gets you pleasantly tipsy. We were greatly amused by one of the young fellows in tight coats. I still haven't learned how to distinguish them from one another and up until tonight felt a natural aversion to both of them, as did most of the boys. Usually these fearful conquerors of Mr. Laomedon come alone or together to the tavern and stay from lunch until closing time; they sit at the bar, drink and keep stone silent, as if oblivious of everyone around them. However, today this young man suddenly tore himself away from the bar, came over to our table and, when everyone had shut up in expectation, broke the silence by ordering a round of drinks for the whole crowd. Then he sat down between Polyphemus and Silenus and stated quietly: "Ee-akk."

At first we all thought he had burped, and Polyphemus, as was his habit, said to him, "How do you do?" However, the young man, somewhat offended, explained that this was his name - Aeacus - and that he was so named in honor of the son of Zeus and Aegina, the father of Telamon and Peleus and grandfather of Greater Aias. Polyphemus immediately made his apologies and proposed a toast to Aeacus's health, so the incident was completely closed. We all introduced ourselves, and very soon Aeacus felt quite at home with us.

He turned out to be a superb raconteur; we simply split our sides listening to him.

We especially like the one about how they soap the floor in the living room, undress the young ladies and have a race for them. They call this "playing touch," and he spoke about it in the drollest manner. I must admit that we all nevertheless felt somewhat embarrassed for our dull backwater, where you would never hear the like of such a thing, and therefore the escapade of the young rowdies from Mr. Nicostratus's band proved to be very timely.

They appeared on the square leading a sizable reddish-orange rooster on a string. Lord, how funny it was! Singing "Nioba-Niobe-ya," they traversed the whole square and came into the tavern. Here they gathered around the bar and ordered brandy for themselves and bluebeer for the rooster. At the same time they announced to the congregation that they were celebrating the rooster's coming of sexual maturity and they invited everyone who wanted to join in. We nearly burst. Aeacus laughed along with us, so that our city, as center of witty entertainments, was somewhat rehabilitated in the eyes of this visitor from the capital.

Achilles arrived with interesting news. He reported that six semiupholstered chairs had been stolen from the courtroom in the town hall. Pandareus had already investigated the scene of the crime and announced that he had found the track. He said there were two burglars, one of them with a velure hat and the other with six toes on his right foot, but actually everyone was certain that the city comptroller had stolen them.

Grouchy Paralus stated straight out: "Looks like he's pulled another fast one. Now everyone will talk about these idiotic chairs and completely forget about his last embezzlement."

When I got home, Charon was still sitting up with his editorial work, and the two of us had supper together.

Just now I looked out the window. The marvelous summer night has fanned over the city a bottomless sky, spangled with myriads of sparkling stars. A warm breeze strews magical aromas and caresses the branches of the slumbering trees. Hush! One can hear the slight buzzing of a lightning bug wandering through the grass, hastening to a rendezvous with his emerald beloved. A benevolent paradise of sleep has lowered onto the little town wearied of its daily labors. No, it still doesn't seem quite right. Well, so be it. Ill just say it was beautiful when high above the huge spaceships, shining with magical lights, passed over our city as symbols of peace and security - you could see at once they weren't ours.

I'm calling my speech "Peace and Certainty," and I'm giving it to Charon for the paper. Just let him try not to print it. That's how it is: the whole city for, and he alone, don't you know, against! It won't work, dear sonnie-in-law, it won't work!

I'm going to Hermione, to see how she feels.